G'day. It's 1:00.
Did the committee agree to come back at 1:00? Was that right, Todd?
Oh, sorry. You're just on mute.
Yes. No problem. Yeah.
No problem.
We were.
And I'm sure with Jamie's fine chairing, are we up to the Lifewise
Trust?
We are. We're right on-
Mate
... on track.
I'll just leave you to it, Jamie.
Okay, looks like we've got Carl. We'll just wait for Carlo and Rima
to join us back.
So far, so good, though?
Great.
Hey, Rima.
Hi, Habib. Hi, team. Hi, Mr. Chair.
Just I was waiting to be let in.
You're all good.
Jamie did okay.
He did all right.
Humble man. Okay, we got Carl and Paulo, got Dan.
We
have a quorum, so I am happy for us to kick on
and start our afternoon session with the Lifewise Trust with Pam
and Anne-Marie, if they could be let in, please.
Hi, Pam.
Hello. How are you?
I'm very good, thank you.
Just getting my camera off. Sorry.
Yeah. That's okay.
And do you have Anne-Marie joining you?
Anne-Marie's here, too.
Oh, there you both are. Fantastic. Lovely to see you both.
Thank you for submitting to us. We have read your submission.
So you have 10 minutes.
Yes.
We would ask that you leave a couple of minutes at the end for questions any of the
members may have. But completely over to you to begin your submission.
Thank you.
Thank you very much. E raeranga tere ma.
Tena koutou, tena koutou, tena koutou katoa.
Ko Wai au. My name's Pam Elgar, and I'm the
CEO of Lifewise and Methodist Mission Northern.
Lifewise is a large social and community service organization in the
Auckland and Rotorua regions. My background includes 20
years of governance in the not-for-profit NGO sector, as well as an
executive career in both public sector banking and
not-for-profit. And I'll hand you over to Anne-Marie.
Kia ora, and thank you for this opportunity.
My name is Anne-Marie Sutcliffe. I'm a registered psychiatric nurse
and general manager of community services for Lifewise and
Methodist Mission Northern. I've got a 40-year history of working in
mental health and community services, as well as working in the public service
sector.
My
services at Lifewise and Methodist Mission Northern sit across a really
broad and connected system for people and whanau, and those
people and whanau are among some of the most vulnerable in our community.
I've got services that work in housing and homelessness responses
and homelessness outreach and family and community services,
early childhood education, and wellbeing support.
We aim to support people with practical pathways back into
connection, safety, and stability.
And together, all of those services work as one system.
We go and we meet people where they are, we build trusted relationships over
time, and we try and link people to the right support so that their immediate
need, their long-term wellbeing, and wider community safety are addressed
together.
Yeah. So we don't intend to repeat the submission.
You've got that. But essentially, we do want to urge the Select
Committee not to support the Summary Offences
Amendment Bill because in our view, it does criminalize rough
sleeping and begging without addressing the root
causes of homelessness, addiction, trauma,
poverty, or mental health need.
In our experience, safer communities are created when
people are supported into safe accommodation with
effective wraparound services, not when they're
displaced from public spaces or pushed into less
visible and less safe places.
Existing legal powers already allow police, council,
and business owners to respond to genuine harm,
including breach of the peace, trespass, obstruction, disorderly
behavior, and breaches of local bylaws.
This bill, in our view, risks undermining years of
trust-based, trauma-informed work between
outreach teams, street whanau, businesses, police, council,
and other community services, while increasing the pressure on the
justice system and public services rather than
delivering better outcomes at a lower cost.
If the bill proceeds, Lifewise strongly recommends that rough
sleeping, intent to inhabit, and begging are
removed as grounds for a move on order, and that police must
first connect people with an accredited social service provider
with additional safeguards for young people under 17 through whanau,
legal guardians, or Oranga Tamariki.
So I want to just talk really briefly about a story from our outreach team, and
this is really talking to the people aspects.
This story's not unusual actually.
It's painfully common. We met a person because they kept
coming back to Merge, our community services cafe on Karanga-a-Hape
Road. That person was sleeping rough.
They'd already been told to move on many, many times.
More times than they can count, actually. They weren't asking for much from us.
They wanted a coffee. They wanted somewhere warm.
They wanted somewhere predictable, and somewhere where they could be seen without
being judged.
But over time with this person, as we got to know them, we learned that being
moved on, to them, didn't feel neutral.
It felt absolutely frightening. They'd lived through trauma in their
past life, and being approached by authority, being told to
leave suddenly, and being treated as a problem when they were
simply trying to survive sent them into a panic.
So they moved, but they didn't move into housing.
They moved into darker, more isolated places.
And it took weeks of consistent contact with us before they trusted
us enough after that experience to talk about getting some support.
And finally that happened, not because we pressured them or threatened them or
demanded compliance, but because we stayed with them.
Same people, time and time again, and we built a relationship,
and they knew that we would still be there tomorrow.
And for us, this is what move on orders risk breaking.
When people are forced to leave familiar places, they don't just disappear.
They become harder to find, harder to help, more
isolated, more afraid, and more at risk.
And importantly, trust gets reset to zero.
So what eventually helped this person wasn't enforcement, it
was relationship, dignity, being known by name, being met
with patience instead of punishment.
And that's why this proposed law worries us, both from a systemic
approach, but also from an operational on the streets approach.
Every day we see safer communities are built by connection,
not by exclusion, by housing people, supporting people,
and staying with people long enough for trust to grow.
For me, the key messages are clear.
Move on orders don't solve homelessness.
Housing and support solves homelessness, and trust is
what makes that change possible.
So what we're asking the committee to be clear about is
what is this bill trying to solve? What's the problem
definition that we're trying to resolve?
And then to be equally clear about what it will actually
do. If a person is rough sleeping, has set up their
belongings, or is sitting quietly with a sign asking for help,
they're not creating homelessness.
They're showing us where homelessness already exists.
Moving them on does not create a home, it doesn't create a health
response, doesn't create an income or a safe place to sleep.
It simply pushes people further from the relationships and
services that can help, and it risks turning poverty,
trauma, and survival into matters for police and the courts.
So our call to action is straightforward.
Do not support this bill in its current form.
At a minimum, remove rough sleeping, intent to inhabit, and begging
as grounds for a move on order.
Require police to connect people with accredited social services
before any enforcement steps are taken, and require stronger
safeguards in place for young people.
The committee has a choice here to endorse a response that
displaces people, or to strengthen one that connects
people to safety, dignity, and support.
We urge you to choose the second path.
Just in closing,
as we mark Matariki, a time for reflection, renewal,
and dreaming of what is possible, Lifewise exhorts the
government and all political parties to work towards a more just
future for everyone in Aotearoa, New Zealand.
That future must be shaped by systems, policies, and public
services that uphold dignity, strengthen
belonging, and create a genuinely human experience for all
people, especially those that are most vulnerable and too
often pushed to the margins. A just society for all
is what we ask for.
We're very happy to answer any questions you might have.
Thanks, Pam. Thank you Anne Marie. Really appreciate it.
We've got two minutes left, so we've got a couple of people wanting to ask
questions. We'll start with Camilla Belich.
Thank you very much for your submission.
It was a really good written submission and oral submission today.
I was just really interested about the public nuisance bylaw that you mentioned
in Auckland, and how you said that that was
implemented in a way that was informed by a trauma
informed approach, and I just wanted to know if you could explain to the
committee what that involves.
In one minute. We're working with the compliance teams who
enact the bylaws in Auckland City, and what that is is about how they engage
with people who are rough sleeping.
There's lots of different ways that you can engage with somebody who's terrified
under a blanket of sleep. You can engage them in a way that doesn't build
trust, or you can work with your outreach teams to actually engage them in a
way that both deals with the behavior and the breaking of the
bylaw, but also builds trust. So you can be pushed
awake by a foot, or you can be woken by somebody who
crouches down and speaks to you gently.
Yeah. And that's obviously the second approach is what we would--
and the bylaws give the possibility of doing that.
There's nothing against that in the bylaws.
Thank you, and Dan Rosewarne.
Thank you, Chair. So you highlighted that when people are moved on, they become
harder to find and harder to help, and I'm keen to just quickly elaborate on
that further. From the perspective of an outreach service, what
impact would that have on your ability to connect people with
housing, healthcare, addiction support, and those other
services?
Yeah. Me?
Yeah.
So our experience is we work in the central Auckland
area, along with Ka Hutia Kaha and Auckland City Mission.
We know where people are, we know who people are, and
we don't double up services. We're very careful about that, but
we know where to go to engage with people.
When people are moved along,
they're going to move out and out and out, and
eventually we predict, in fact, we're almost seeing it already,
that people are going to move to places where they're harder to be moved on.
It's a frightening experience to be moved on by the police for
people, anybody really, but particularly people with a trauma history.
What will happen, we predict, is that, in fact, we're already seeing it a little
bit, is that people will move from where we find them, accessible and
regular,
to a stream, to a
bush. We've heard of people going bush in Henderson, places like
that,
to places where it's much, much harder and less efficient pragmatically for our
outreach services to find them.
Thank you.
Thank you. And thank you, Pam and Anne-Marie.
We really appreciate your time in coming to submit to us today, so thank you.
No problem at all. All the best with your mahi.
Thank you.
Okay, we're now onto Extension Rebellion Ōtepoti, and we've got
Jen Olsen.
Hey, Jen. Thank you for-
Hey
... joining us this afternoon. We can see you and hear you nice and clearly.
Jen, you've got 10 minutes. We'd love it if you left a few minutes at the end for
some of the members to ask questions if they have them. But over to you, Jen.
Okay. Thank you. Kia ora koutou ko Jen Olsen
toku ingoa. Thanks for the opportunity.
And, yeah, I'd really like to endorse the two previous
speakers.
I worked in social services for over 30 years,
including as a mental health support worker and as a social worker.
And I'm also a climate activist, and I see
links between the social justice issues that are raised by this bill,
the effects of colonization, and the climate and ecological
emergency.
I'm opposed to this Summary Offences Bill.
I see it as an attempt to conceal the consequences
of the failure of our society to provide the basic necessities of
life for everyone.
And that failure is just one symptom of the failure of our
economic system,
which has not only failed to deliver homes for all our citizens,
it's failed to honor Crown obligations to Māori,
failed to reduce the emissions that are leading to catastrophic climate
change, and it's failed to protect our environments from
biodiversity loss and ecological breakdown.
But anyway, to return to the bill,
my concerns include the vulnerability of youth,
disregard for the principles of totality, and the callous
attitude towards some of the least fortunate members of our
society.
The evidence from the University of Otago reports that nearly half
of all homeless people in Aotearoa are aged under
25. Most are homeless due to circumstances
outside of their control, such as family violence,
poverty, and overcrowding.
And youth may not comply with move on orders simply because there
is nowhere safe for them to go. Youth that have aged out of
Oranga Tamariki care, two-thirds of whom are Māori,
may have no whanau support, and the services for homeless
youth are extremely limited.
The Waitangi Tribunal in 2023 found that the
Crown had breached the principles of equity and active
protection in its lack of support for homeless rangatahi,
and this bill compounds that breach.
Research has consistently also shown that contact with the justice
system in adolescence leads to more frequent contact
later in life. So this bill increases the long-term risk for
homeless youth.
Criminalizing people who are in public places for safety reasons
or who are unable to comply with police due to mental distress
or cognitive issues when there are simply not enough resources
in the community to support them, it's unfair and it's
wrong.
The Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Psychiatrists, the
Mental Health and Wellbeing Commission, and the Mental Health Foundation have
all highlighted in recent years increasing levels of mental
distress, particularly amongst young people,
and that the mental health services in Aotearoa are not
meeting those needs.
Nothing has substantially changed since
2023, when a report from 500 mental health
physicians concluded that the mental health
services in Aotearoa are not fit for purpose.
So yeah, this is something I've witnessed at first hand, the lack of
resources and the difficulty finding affordable and
supported accommodation for people with mental illness or with learning
disabilities. Workers in mental health do everything they can,
but there's no substitute for comprehensive and
properly resourced services. That's what we need.
Our services are fragmented.
They are siloed due to moves to tighten eligibility
criteria and funding over the years.
No one has the responsibility to follow through with an individual
and ensure that that person's needs are met.
Radio New Zealand reported just the other day that each month for the
past 16 months, there were 1,000 more
inquiries to MSD about emergency
housing than there were actual formal
applications submitted.
That's 1,000 people out there needing help
who didn't even get through to applying for it.
And for those who did make it to a formal application and were
declined, a third were offered nothing.
Nothing at all.
And these are issues well known to frontline workers like police.
Giving police powers to ask people to move on is just shifting the problem from
one place to another. We have citizens of Aotearoa
homeless and unwell in our streets.
About a third of homeless people are Maori, tangata whenua of
this land, suffering from the long-term effects of colonization,
loss of land, livelihood, and community, and we are just telling them to
go away. Brunis Hickey reported
that this government is currently building more prison beds than
beds in affordable homes.
That's a disgrace. It brings shame to this government and anyone who
supports this heartless legislation.
We know that there are not enough affordable homes in Aotearoa.
It's the result of housing being used for many years as an investment
and new kainga ora projects being stopped.
Over 3,000 planned new builds were stopped by this government.
Public housing is not an optional extra for society.
It's an essential service to provide all our citizens a
life of dignity.
Research evidence in Aotearoa shows unequivocally that the
answer to homelessness is support into suitable housing.
Well, who knew? Aotearoa is a rich
country, and the rich are becoming more and more wealthy.
The collective wealth of the country's 150 richest
individuals and families has grown, this is
mind-boggling, by $26.9 billion
in one year.
This is obscene when people are homeless and begging on the streets.
Poverty is increasing. The New Zealand Council of Christian
Social Services has shown that there are
473,000 people in Aotearoa
right now experiencing material hardship.
Poverty is the result of deliberate policies that have increased the gap between
rich and poor, such as maintaining levels of unemployment as a
strategy to reduce inflation, encouraging the use of housing as an
investment, and allowing virtual monopolies on food
supplies, privatizing services, user pays.
The list goes on. And now this government wants to hide the
results by moving people who demonstrate the
failure of their policies out of sight so we don't have to
look at the human cost.
What is the economy for if it is not to provide for the people of
Aotearoa, to provide the necessities of life, shelter
being the very first? An economy that fails to do that is a
failure, no matter what the books say.
So we see the parallel consequences resulting from government
policies focusing on a narrow view of economy
and growth. We see increased poverty and social injustice
alongside increasing wealth and the influence of an elite few.
We have blatant breaches of good faith surrounding Te Tiriti o
Waitangi alongside claims of equality in society,
and we have increasing climate-related emergencies and
threatened extinctions of our endemic wildlife alongside a
disregard for emissions reduction, plans to enable more
extractive industries, and treatment of the environment as a
disposable resource.
We're in the midst of a polycrisis that's not only a social
crisis like the one of homelessness and poverty, but an
environmental one of rising temperatures and unstable weather
events, and an international political crisis of
wars, resource scarcity, and displaced people.
Aotearoa cannot separate itself from the rest of the world in this and can't
deny that our social problems and our environmental problems are
linked by our political attitude.
The same short-term policies of exploitation and
prioritization of financial gain have resulted in the social
injustices we see in colonization, homelessness, and
the climate and ecological emergency we are all facing.
This legislation is in the same spirit as climate denial,
and I'm asking you now, reject this bill in its
entirety. Thank you.
Thanks, Jen, and thank you for your oral submission.
We have
time for one question if anybody would be interested to ask.
That's quite all right. It's not a reflection on your submission, Jen.
We have-
No, I didn't expect any questions. It's pretty clear-cut really, isn't it?
We thank you for your time, Jen. Thanks for coming in.
You're very welcome. Thanks for listening.
No problem.
Okay.
Thank you.
Bye.
All right. We're now going to have Pamela Greeley coming
on,
so we'll just wait for her to come online.
Hey, Pamela. Thank you for joining us today.
We have read your submission.
You've got five minutes, and if you'd like to leave a little bit of time at the end
for questions, we would welcome that. But over to you.
Kia ora koutou. Ko Pamela Grilli toku ingoa.
Thank you for the opportunity to speak.
I do want to start by acknowledging that businesses, retailers, and members of the
public do sometimes experience intimidating or
disruptive behavior in public places.
Those concerns are real, and they do deserve to be taken seriously.
However, I don't believe this bill addresses the cause of those problems.
It simply addresses their visibility.
The bill mistakes homelessness for the problem.
Rough sleeping and begging are usually symptoms of housing insecurity,
trauma, mental illness, addiction or poverty, or
other circumstances. Moving someone from one street to another doesn't
solve any of these things. It simply relocates the problem.
I live in the beautiful Coromandel, and we are seeing people,
either of their own volition because they're already being moved on, we're seeing
more and more homelessness in Coromandel, and we don't have the infrastructure to
deal with them. We have very small community services who
are, again, being
pulled apart by these because they just don't have the resources to deal with
them.
Sorry, lost my place here.
My own experience has been that people sleeping rough often want something very
simple. They want to just be treated like people.
I always acknowledge them if they're asking for food or money, and I'm in a
position to help with whatever their request is, I will.
But I've found that simply acknowledging them, saying hello, and recognizing their
humanity is just as important.
This bill treats people experiencing homelessness
primarily as a public order problem.
I believe we should first recognize them as members of our community who deserve
dignity and support.
And finally, I find it difficult to reconcile this bill with the government's focus
on reducing public spending. During COVID, we
demonstrated that providing emergency accommodation significantly reduced
rough sleeping. If we reduce housing support, move people on, and
then imprison them for breaching a move on order, we are choosing one of the
most expensive responses available.
Housing people costs money. Imprisoning them costs considerably
more.
I believe New Zealand can do better than moving vulnerable people from place to
place. We should be investing in solutions that help people regain stability
rather than criminalizing them for being homeless.
I only had a tube of wine gums for lunch, sorry.
Before I finish, I'd ask the committee to remember that the
people affected by this bill are not strangers.
They are our neighbors, our workmates, our friends, our rangatahi, and
sometimes our whānau. Many New Zealanders are only a few setbacks away
from housing insecurity. A lost job, an illness, a
relationship breakdown, or an unexpected expense can change
someone's circumstances remarkably quickly.
I hope any response to homelessness reflects that shared humanity and
focuses on helping people regain stability rather than simply moving
them on. Thank you.
Thank you, Pamela. I will just see if there are-- Yeah, there are a couple of
members with questions. We've got time for both of them, so we'll start with
Camilla Belich.
I'll let Lawrence go first because I've had a few first questions.
Dr Lawrence Yun.
Cool. Thank you so much, Chair. Thank you for that submission, Pamela.
I think my question, and something that we've been asking for a
little while, which is in your area, particularly in Coromandel, being more
rural and regional,
the experience might be different.
If people are moved on, would you know where would they be moving
to? And for example, then what sort of services would they
likely then have or not have because they've been moved on?
So they don't have their whānau support.
We have a number of
501s.
We have a number of people with mental illnesses that we know in town.
We know who they are. They spend a lot of time moving between different
rohe. I often pick them up hitchhiking because
they've decided they're going to go somewhere else.
We don't have enough emergency housing.
Emergency housing is really hard to come by in Coromandel.
We're 50% holiday homes. There are not a lot of
free houses.
So basically, we're
trying to help the people that we know because they are part of our community.
And we know when they disappear for a few days, they've just relocated themselves.
You see them standing on the side of
State Highway 25 with their thumbs out.
So it's a real challenge for us as much as it is for
people in the cities and the towns.
Thank you.
Right. And Camilla?
Thanks. Just a question. Thanks for your well-written submission.
I really like the bit where you talked about how people don't realize
sometimes how close people are to homelessness.
Mm-hmm.
And I don't think we've focused on this in question so much, but that's reflected
in some of the submissions, I think, that described
homelessness as a domino. And so I just wanted to give you the opportunity to
expand on that. I think sometimes there's this tendency to
other homelessness, but actually it may affect more people in our community than
we realize. So I just wanted to see if you wanted to expand on that.
Yeah. Again, we see that we're also very poorly served for
regular full-time work in
rural areas a lot of the time.
People are surviving on next to nothing.
When benefits are cut, when they can't afford to put petrol in their cars, when
all of these things happen,
they lose their jobs. And then again, they lose their homes because
there's no other way for them to get any money other than by a
benefit, and they can't get to their benefit appointments because there's nothing
locally. They have to go
to the nearest town, which is about an hour away, no public transport.
So we can see how that's all happening. Like you say, it's a domino.
The domino effect is real, and it's closer than you think.
Great. Thank you, Pamela. Really appreciate you writing both a written
submission and presenting to us today.
So thank you very much for your time, and enjoy the beautiful Coromandel as well.
Thank you.
Great. Okay. We have got Sheree, who's now going to be presenting
to us.
Oh, okay. I can see Matthew. Ah, we
don't have Sheree yet. Okay. We will carry on, and we will go to Matthew instead.
Hey, Matthew. Thank you for joining us. Appreciate you being here.
You got five minutes. We've read your submission, but please do leave time at the
end for some questions as well. But totally over to you.
Okay. Thank you, everyone. Look, I want to start off by thanking the select
committee for allowing me to submit on this bill, and congratulations also to
you, Mr. Chair, for your recent promotion. So my name is Matthew De Rossini.
I'm a local student here in Ōtautahi, and I organized the
opposition to the Move On orders, bill when it was first announced.
So I had the great privilege of hosting a rally and a space to
support and amplify the voices of our homeless community here at Christchurch.
And it was those voices that inform my submission today.
So I've been listening to the submissions this morning.
I've heard overwhelmingly, as I hope the committee has as well, that
there is not a good amount of support for this bill from the New Zealand public.
I want to talk with the submission of Terangi Cleaver when she asked, "Move on
where? Where are these move on orders supposed to apply to?" I
also want to talk with the submission of Sharon Halborn, who spoke of the
importance of love and compassion when solving the issues we have in society.
In my written submission, I did recommend that a nonpartisan approach should be
taken to address issues such as homelessness.
And so it is really sad to see certain members of this committee using submissions
as an excuse to launch attacks on the opposition.
I want to start my own submission by saying that I want to see a New Zealand where
every single person has safety and dignity in what they need to thrive, and
that does include us business owners as well.
And that's precisely why I don't support this bill.
This bill touches upon a complex issue that is a result of
systematic failures. All evidence points to the fact that this bill will not solve
an issue, but will instead displace it.
And I think of the gentleman living rough on the streets of my suburb in
Riccarton. He moved away from the city center because police have already begun
moving on homeless people from the city center.
This bill will isolate people. Here in Christchurch, we have the red zone, which is
the block of land abandoned after the white earthquake.
It's a dangerous piece of land with roaming dogs and live electricity, as well as a
complete isolation from the support services that many people rely on.
Despite this, there is already an established homeless community in the red zone,
and it's a community that is struggling.
They are sick, they are cold, and they go about.
This bill will push more people to the red zone, and it will kill people.
I do not want this bill to proceed in any form, but in light of the government's
insistence to continue with it, I do want the select committee to seriously
consider whether applying
bill to rough sleeping and begging is the
best course of action. We know that these sections make the bill inconsistent with
the Bill of Rights Act. Official advice has consistently urged the government to
drop these parts of the bill.
If this bill does continue unamended, it will paint an incredibly sad
portrait of our nation. I grew up in a country where we cared for people, and I
don't know where that's gone.
That's all I have to say to the committee. I'm happy to take any questions.
Thank you very much.
Thank you, Matthew, and thank you for your very well-considered
submission. Really appreciate it. I've got a question from Rima Naklay.
Kia ora, Matthew. Thanks for your submission and for caring.
Hey, look, you started off by saying that this bill doesn't do anything to solve
homelessness. On what basis do you feel
that this bill is meant to solve homelessness?
Where'd you get that understanding from, Matthew?
No, so this bill, I don't believe that this bill is intended to solve homelessness.
I think ultimately we have an issue in this country.
It's an issue that's at its highest reported level according to many
community providers. We need to be addressing this issue, and
the proposals that are being brought about by this government at the moment,
such as this bill, for the most part, do not address the issues that we're seeing
in our country.
Okay. I'll let Camilla. I had another question, but all good.
Thanks, Matthew.
Camilla.
Thanks. Thanks for your submission, and for the work that you've been doing on this
bill. The question I had, you mentioned
homelessness and rough sleeping, but another area which has come up a wee bit in
the submissions on this bill and in the commentary has been the impact on
young people 14 to 18. Did you have, and sorry if I
missed it in your written submission, any comment to make on the inclusion of that
group?
Yeah. Well, a lot of the people I see on the streets of Ōtautahi are young
people.
And I just cannot understand why
this bill applies to 14-year-olds.
I think these are people who are so vulnerable.
We need to be supporting them. We need to be providing them with adequate social
services and wraparound support, and this bill just does not address
that at all.
Thanks, Matthew. Thank you very much for both your written and your oral submission
and coming before us today. Really appreciate it. So thank you.
Kia ora. Thank you.
All right. Members, we've got Sheree Fluntoff now, so we'll just have
Sheree promoted.
Hey, Sheree. Thank you for joining us today. There you are.
We can see you. You're on mute, but thank you very much for coming before us.
We have read your submission. You have five minutes, so please do leave a little
bit of time at the end, and we may ask you some questions, but in your
hands.
Thank you, Tom, and hello, members of the committee.
I've come on not as an expert in the area of homelessness,
but as someone who does understand how policy can and should
work,
and also someone who has strong feelings on how we should treat
those that are most vulnerable.
Because we're not a country that believes in kicking people when they are down.
There are penalties already for illegal behavior.
We do not need to criminalize being homeless, which
is in itself an incredibly vulnerable
position to be in. And there's so many things that can cause
homelessness, whether it's mental health, relationship breakdowns,
death of a loved one, ill health. There's just so
many different things that people are already dealing with.
I personally would not want to be sleeping out in the cold, even in Tauranga,
which
does have quite a mild climate.
I feel so sorry for the people that do have to deal with that already,
and do not believe that we should be
making that a crime. I also do feel for the shopkeepers who find
it challenging to have
homeless people outside their shops.
And I think the only reasonable response to that
would be to give people somewhere better to go.
So instead of criminalizing
finding somewhere warm
and sheltered to hang out in
bad or even good weather, we should be looking at how we can
give them somewhere better to go. And if we are really sensible about it
and want to use our resources wisely,
making sure that we're giving them some of those social supports like mental
health treatment,
somewhere to live,
good food to eat, and the opportunity to get
themselves into a place where they can actually sustain
paying their own way, getting a job, contributing to
the society more, rather than just criminalizing them and giving
ourselves more ongoing costs in the process of doing so
for housing them in prisons instead of working towards them being
productive members of society. So yeah, if
we're going to have a bill about homelessness, it should be about making sure that
we're putting those supports in place to reduce the problem and to give them
somewhere else to go, because they're not going to hang around in shop doorways if
there's somewhere better for them, are they?
Anyway, that's
pretty much the point I wish to make.
Just to add that voice so that you know how many people out here in the
country are concerned that we don't want to kick those that are most vulnerable
when they're already down.
So
yeah.
Thank you, Sheree. Thank you, and good to see another Tauranga local.
So,
got a question from Dr. Lawrence Sun Han.
Cool. Thank you, Chair. Thank you Sheree, for your submission.
I think one of the things the committee has heard today is
around the balance between safety and
wellbeing of homeless whanau, but as far as ensuring that
business owners and customers are safe as well,
when you do see aggressive behavior.
Can I check, do you think when businesses are
raising concerns around potentially
behavior issues or even rough sleeping or homelessness, that their
intention is for them to be incarcerated and criminalized,
as opposed to finding accommodations or finding the
wraparound support that they actually need?
I think there's a couple of different questions within that.
Mm.
So, aggressive behavior can be addressed with
existing laws.
It's a separate issue altogether.
Getting them to move on,
I think a lot of the business owners just want them to be somewhere else.
The problem with this bill is that it is very much
criminalizing a state of being rather than
criminalizing a behavior, and it's not about
actually investing
in getting people
alternatives. So helping them want to be somewhere else,
helping them have the skills and the backstops
of housing and mental health support and other things that they might
need to be able to be somewhere else.
So yeah, this bill very much is just about the rough sleeping, not about the
aggressive behaviors. And
I think a lot of people are just so focused on,
"Don't have them in front of my shop," that they don't actually think about what
those flow on effects might be to police
resources, to court resources, to prison resources,
and of course, to the actual homeless people themselves who are already in a
very vulnerable position, particularly the young ones.
But any homeless person.
Thank you.
Thank you, Sheree. I see my colleague Carl Bates has his hands up.
We've very limited time, but Carl.
Thanks, Chair, and thanks, Sheree.
Your comment that this criminalizes homelessness, isn't the
step first of requiring the individual to move
on, and in the case of Whanganui, that might be to go down to the Crisis Cafe,
which has been set up to support people who have some of these
challenges, to find those resources they need in our city,
exactly what we're trying to achieve here?
Both supporting the businesses that are having their
trade interrupted and helping that individual find the support they need.
In this case, it is really about
giving the police extra powers to move people on, where they wouldn't do so to the
rest of us.
Like
normal people, we don't want to be a society where the police can just tell us to
move because they don't like us, because we're standing outside
protesting something, or because we're hanging around a
little bit long and they-
Don't want their customers to think that
we belong there or whatever.
It's just about picking on a particular group, but it is going against those
civil liberties that all of us take for granted.
And in most places, there's not somewhere open
24/7 that's close to the facilities and resources that
people who are homeless need.
I mean, a lot of people, and I did compliment our Tauranga
library.
I did notice one day when I was in there that some of the homeless people were
coming in to be able to charge their cell phones and just sit there quietly.
They weren't causing any problems, and they were reading the newspaper
and just having somewhere that they could go that was under
shelter and warm, but it's not open 24/7.
Homeless people also need places to shelter when
cafes are closed, when libraries are closed.
And
if we are providing places that are more attractive and better for
them, then most of them will actually end up going there instead of sleeping in a
doorway because it's the only comfortable,
and I use the word comfortable loosely, unlike my cat, who someone commented on
earlier, who is comfortable.
But yes, I use the word
comfortable loosely when sleeping in a doorway is not
exactly what most of us would choose.
But if you give them better places, they will naturally gravitate
towards them. So, that's what we should be focusing our resources on.
Thank you, Sheree. Really appreciate you submitting to us today, and also for your
written submission to us as well. Thank you for your time.
Thank you, Tom.
Okay. We now have Susan Bagshaw, who's going to be
speaking to us.
Hey, Sue.
Hey.
Thank you.
Kia ora, Tom. Good to see you. I'll just put my camera on. Hold on.
Thank you very much.
Okay.
Great. Oh, nearly there.
Nearly there.
Be great.
Got it.
Thanks for giving me the opportunity to speak to this bill.
I want to make four points. I'm by trade a doctor, so my first
point is health in terms of it's impossible to be
healthy and provide healthcare as a doctor if someone hasn't got a home.
If they're living on the street, it's
totally predictable that they will be unwell.
Second point is that being on the street and sleeping
rough is not a life choice.
People are there not by choice. If they had the choice, they wouldn't be there,
but because there's no other choice.
Thirdly, I'd love to see the government putting in opening up
emergency housing.
We did it in COVID, we can do it again, so that people do have an
alternative, not just special places like the youth hub here in
Christchurch or places in
Wanganui and Whangarei.
And fourthly, I would love to see an alternative which is feasible,
and that's building more state housing, and that's my other position that I'm
speaking from today as part of a group in Ōtautahi which is
really campaigning hard to build more state housing.
Affordable housing is not affordable.
Not on a benefit, not if you're sick, not if you're young,
on casual wages, on low income. So we need state
housing in order to give people an opportunity to get a
home and then move up. Without a home, you can't
do that.
So happy to answer questions.
Fantastic, Sue. Thank you very much, and very well put and very succinct.
So thank you.
First question from one of your Christchurch locals, Dan Rosewarne.
Hey, Sue. Thanks for that submission.
And I just want to elaborate on the
connection between health and housing, because as a doctor, you've
seen firsthand that connection. And I was just wondering if you could explain a bit
more about what your experience tells you about the likely health
impacts of moving people on from public spaces compared
to providing stable housing and support, if that was
possible.
Absolutely. It's very much linked to employment because what we found
was after the earthquake,
about four or five organizations in Ōtautahi got together and said,
"What can we do about housing for young people?"
Because obviously I'm a youth health provider.
And
what we came up with is
looking at trying to get temporary housing.
We got people into housing,
but then what happened was that they were not having permanent
housing or stable housing. They were couch surfing, they were staying with
friends, they were staying in emergency night shelters.
They got a job, but then they couldn't keep that job because they kept moving,
and they didn't have transport.
So because we did both, we helped them into housing and employment.
And you just can't keep a job if you're not in stable
housing.
Thanks, Sue.
Great. Well, thank you, Sue. Really appreciate both your written and your oral
submission, and for coming before us today. Thank you very much for your time.
Thank you. And my last comment is please don't let
this amendment go through. It would be unjust.
And let's do an amendment that says let's build more state housing. Thank you.
Thank you, Sue. Have a good afternoon.
Thank you.
We're now going to have a submission from Arthur Bindy and
Katrina.
Katarina, sorry.
If they aren't here, then
I have seen...
Yeah. Anne. We might jump to Anne, and then we can come back to the fans there.
We can just promote her.
Hello, can you hear me?
We can, Anne.
Great.
Thank you for being with us today. You've got five minutes.
We've read your submission,
so please just leave a little bit of time at the end for some questions any of the
members may have. But over to you.
Ngā mihi. Kia ora. Thank you.
So my submission on the Move On legislation is that
legislation should be in the interests of everyone.
The legislation will carve off sections of our society and is therefore
not legislation for everyone. Unfortunately, it reeks of
fascism and is an attack on social cohesion.
Next, the government will be wanting to fence people out of our city centers and
have checkpoints to get in. Does that remind you of anywhere?
Palestine.
I recommend you scrap this Move On legislation and bring back sufficient
social housing, food banks, et cetera.
People have the right to be able to move around New Zealand freely.
Singling out a group of people via legislation is a disgrace,
as well as difficult to implement.
Asking police to single people out, make arrests based on whether a person
looks homeless or is causing a disturbance,
will impact our whole society. For example, under the Bill
of Rights,
protesters are able to protest about injustices across New
Zealand and the world. Police could be confused whether a
person is homeless, causing a disturbance, or simply
defending the rights of the homeless, or anyone
else for that matter.
This legislation is effectively moving on the government's
responsibility for its citizens
to the police, which will only serve to separate people from each
other. This is often referred to as a police state.
The only thing here that should be moved on is this piece of
legislation. I'm happy to take questions.
Fantastic, Anne. Thank you very much.
I will look to see if any members have any questions. We have a question from Dr.
Lawrence Sunan.
Cool. Thank you so much, Chair. And thank you so much for
your submission. I think
your point around what next is a really
important one, I think for the select committee to also kind of consider.
But I guess my question to you then is
what then would be the solution, right?
We know the-
Well-
Yeah. Okay.
Yeah. So the solution is... Oh, sorry, you finish your question?
I have, sorry.
Okay.
Yeah, that is my concern, is the what next.
And some of this sort of fascist type of
police state legislation does lead to far bigger
problems, and that's why I talked about social cohesion.
Aotearoa is a place where we all look out for each
other. If we start singling out people and saying, "Oh, they're homeless.
Oh, quick, move them away. We don't want the tourists to see that,"
it leads to all sorts of problems. I mean, look at
apartheid in South Africa. Look at Nazism in Germany.
I mean, those things started somewhere, and I don't want to be living
in a country where that sort of social separation starts to happen.
So the solution is, as the doctor previously was talking about,
social housing, having places for people to go to.
People aren't homeless by choice.
These are things that have happened to them,
that we should therefore be able to happen for them to
be able to have somewhere safe to go, to be able to get better or find
somewhere to live, that kind of thing.
We should be a caring society, not one where we just move people from one
spot to another. And I fear that that will lead to much
larger problems. Whether it takes a couple of months
or five years, it will lead to far greater problems for
this country.
Cool. Appreciate the insight. Thanks, Anne.
Fantastic. Well, thank you, Anne, and really appreciate both your written and your
oral submission, and coming before us today.
So thank you very much for your time.
You're welcome.
Okay. We're going to go and hear from Arthur, Bindy, and
Katarina.
Yeah.
Now.
Yes.
There we go.
Afternoon. We can see and hear you. Nice to see you all.
Thank you for joining us this afternoon.
You have five minutes. We have read your submission.
But please do leave a little bit of time at the end for some questions from the
members if you can. Over to you.
Kia ora. My name's Arthur Clayton, and I've been a volunteer at the
City Mission for over four years now.
And over that time, I've got to meet people like this, people who've
become good friends. All this discussion and these people who are saying
great things to your committee, but this is the voice of the people that you
are affecting.
And so I'm just going to ask two questions.
I'll focus it on Bindy, but anyone in this group may want to
answer, or if you have a question, they can answer.
So Bindy, just to start off, what is it like to be living on the
streets?
It's like taking your last breath
We're humans.
It's not taking your heart, but last bit, we're humans.
It's hard out there. It's very hard out there for us, and we know
it's hard out there for the community as well.
But all we're trying to do is survive like everyone else.
Mm.
We're only trying to survive.
We're hoping to have hope.
We're hoping to have a lot of compassion out there, and most of
all, love. No matter
who we are, no matter what we are, we're human beings too.
Kia ora.
Also, if you were to enforce this,
as you are doing by law before the election comes into place, how do other
countries address this type of issue with move on orders?
We've got bigger countries out there addressed this kind of issue.
How do they look at this with fairness and dignity and independence, with the
homelessness given the situations that we've been in,
the harsh elements. How do other countries do this?
I mean, we're only a small country compared to other country.
Move on orders even blocking the entrances to shops and
businesses. It's not by choice.
We're dependents. How do other countries approach this?
So, Bindy, how do you cope on the
streets? What do people do?
We use to keep warm.
Mm.
We,
drugs to keep us going.
We haven't got choices to be where we are today.
If we have a bit of compassion, being in the housing, most of
all, have someone to... It's pretty hard when you get the housing,
because don't forget, we've come from homeless.
We've come from people that we are always around all the time, so we
need support. We need 24-hour support. It's like a baby.
When you bring a baby to the house, you need to nurture that baby.
Well, it's just like a homeless. It's the same thing.
And all we need is some compassion. We're humans.
Let us breathe. Let us live again.
And what's the answer?
What's the advice that anyone here would give to the committee for what they
should be doing
to get to solve this homelessness?
Talk to us.
Communicate with us. We are normal people like everyone else.
Mm.
Yes, we are homeless, and we are on the streets asking for money.
But we don't force people to give us money, we just accept what they give
us, like 50 cents, $50.
Please, I urge the MPs to please listen to us.
We don't want this bill to come through, please, because it's going to affect us.
So you've heard, this is a very short piece of time, and this group would have
loved to have come to Parliament so you can meet them in person and
look at them, kanohi ki kanohi.
Mm.
I have a question just to finish off, and then we'll answer any questions that you
have. But my question to the committee is: Is
there anything in this proposed bill that will help those without a home
get a home? Kia ora.
Fantastic. Thanks, Arthur, Bindy, and to the rest of you, thank you so
much for your submission today. We do have a
question from Camilla Belich.
Thank you all so much for your submission.
It's really powerful to hear from you, and we have been listening to you
today as well. So thank you very much
for your written submission and also for speaking to us and answering those
questions. I just had a question around the bill.
With your experience that you've all had and your different
lives that you've had and the different roles that you've had, if this bill was to
pass, what would the additional struggles be on someone
who
received a move on order who was homeless?
What would be the additional challenges, do you think?
Answer this one for you. It creates conflict where conflict isn't
necessary between us and, say, security,
the guards, police officers.
Where you could probably address that where the police with just disorderly
behavior for those aggressive people that are on the street, you don't necessarily
need another element to move everybody along.
It would just take a lot of the conflict and the aggression away from diffusing the
situation, I suppose.
Thank you. Thanks so much for your submission.
I'm sorry, Lawrence, but we are out of time on that one. I'm sorry.
But I just want to say a big thank you to all of you for
fronting up today and for making both a written and oral submission to us as a
committee. We really do appreciate it. So thank you.
Thank you for listening. Kia ora.
Thank you very much.
Kia ora. Thank you for listening.
Come make the right decision.
Kia ora.
Okay. We're now going to move to Anika Green.
And Anika is with us. Hello.
Tena koutou katoa.
Thanks for joining us. We've read your submission.
You've got five minutes, and please leave a little bit of time at the end for any
questions.
Amazing. Thank you. Tena koutou katoa.
My name is Anika Green. I'm a 21-year-old youth worker from Poneke,
Wellington, a recent graduate from Victoria University, and a member of the St.
Thomas' Church in Newtown.
I ask you to reject this bill in its entirety.
I'm not here because this is an abstract policy debate.
I'm here because I know the people that this bill will affect.
People with names, people with stories, people whose lives have already been
shaped by poverty, trauma, mental illness, addictions, and
systems that have failed to protect them.
I grew up in a Christian community called Still Waters that shared life with whanau
living on the streets, and later, my family lived in social housing
alongside families at risk of homelessness.
Through my church communities over the years, I have spent years sharing meals,
conversation, laughter, and friendship with people sleeping rough in
Wellington. That's a pretty unique experience for a 21-year-old.
In Newtown, where I live and volunteer, I see homelessness every
day. I see addiction and severe mental distress.
These are not strangers to me. They are neighbors.
They are people I know by name Last year, the headline in
Newtown was that homelessness had reached a 24-year high.
24 years, and this is our response.
I was in the gallery for the first reading, and it made me absolutely weep, not
because I disagree with this bill in theory, but because I was imagining
those exact people who this bill's going to make life harder for.
As a Christian, I believe every person carries a God-given dignity.
It cannot be earned or lost. Every human being holds it equally.
This is why I find this bill so deeply disturbing.
This bill suggests the problem is not a lack of housing, untreated trauma,
addiction, mental health struggles, poverty, or decades of
under-investment. Instead, it suggests the problem is that vulnerable
people can be seen. I reject that completely.
Homelessness is not a crime. It is evidence of a collective
failure. By the time someone is sleeping rough or begging on a
footpath, society has already failed them many, many times.
The answer to collective failure cannot be individual punishment.
I want safe streets more than anyone.
As someone who works to create safe spaces for young people each and every
week, I deeply care about public safety.
But safety is not built on exclusion,
and there is nothing compassionate or successful about streets that appear
cleaner because we've pushed vulnerable people somewhere else.
Hidden suffering is still suffering.
The measure of a society is not how well it hides poverty, it is how
it responds to it.
Because it does not build a single home, it does not provide addiction
treatment, it does not fund mental health care, it does not heal
trauma. It simply tells people to move on.
Move on to where? Where does someone go when they have no one
to go?
As a youth worker, I think of the young people I work with every week, the
14-year-olds who are incredibly vulnerable.
14-year-olds that could be impacted by this bill.
Homelessness does not begin in adulthood.
It begins with the years of unmet need, poverty, instability,
and being failed. If we respond to poverty with punishment instead of
care,
then we are not solving the problem.
We are ensuring it continues.
And so as I prepared this submission, I thought about 14-year-olds I
work with. What would I say to them if their life fell apart, if they lost
their home, if their world unraveled?
Would our country's answer really be, "Move on or face a fine or
prison if you don't"? I never, ever want that to be the message we
send to any young person.
This bill is not only morally wrong, it is contradicted by the evidence.
We know Housing First works. We know stable housing reduces
offending. We know people recover when they are given safety,
stability, and support. Compassion is not naive.
It is effective.
I speak before you today as a youth worker, a Christian, a
young New Zealander who deeply cares about the future of this
country. The decisions made here will shape the future that my
generation inherits. I want to inherit a
country that refuses to confuse poverty with criminality,
a country that refuses to punish people simply for being poor,
a country that understands dignity belongs to everyone.
So I leave you with one question: Years from now, when future
generations ask how New Zealand responded to these people who are
so incredibly vulnerable,
what story do we want to tell?
That when people were at their most vulnerable, we moved them on,
or we met suffering with courage? That we chose housing over
displacement, compassion over punishment, and hope over
fear? That we remembered every person's dignity even when it was
inconvenient.
I know which New Zealand I want to help build.
I hope this committee chooses it, too. Thank you.
Thank you, Anika. And that is right on the five minutes.
All good.
So we really do appreciate both your written and your oral submission, and the
really clear message that you have sent today.
So thank you for your time, and thank you for your work as well.
No worries. See you.
Okay. We are now onto our next submitter, which is Marie.
Hi, Marie. Thank you for joining us today.
Hoping you might be able to unmute yourself.
There we go.
Thank you very much for submitting to us. We have read your submission.
You have five minutes. Please do leave a little bit of time at the end for any
questions members may have. But over to you.
Kia ora, good afternoon. This isn't in my submission, but I do want
to note that some members of the committee and
Parliament identify as Christians,
and I want to address them. I think Mr.
Arbuckle, who was chairing this morning, said in Parliament a while ago
that he was not particularly religious, but that he respected
the Christian tradition. And Mr. Garcia, I think who's in your
committee, is described online as a devout Christian, and I'm sure there are
others.
Now, I have no religion myself, but I have some familiarity with the New
Testament and the life of Christ.
In the years of his ministry, Jesus was a homeless person.
He had no fixed abode. He would be called today a couch surfer, staying
overnight with friends.
And of course, at the time Jesus was born, his parents were rough sleepers.
They had no home.
They only got into the stable because there was a woman about to give birth.
And today, the equivalent would be a garage, I think.
So it's not surprising that Jesus Christ's message is very much one
of care and compassion for the poor, the afflicted,
and the homeless. And I know a Christian by their works.
We saw some this morning from the Christchurch Methodist Mission.
They were heard by your committee
So ask committee members and all members of Parliament who identify as Christian,
are they comfortable with the prospect of being known as
hypocrites if they pass this bill?
Because if they vote for this bill, they are hypocrites.
They're not true to their religion.
In biblical language, they're called whited sepulchers.
And finally, anyone with even a slight interest in politics in
this country can see what's going on, what the coalition government
is doing,
adopting act after act and bill after bill and policy
after policy that seek to pit different groups in society against
each other.
For example, employers against low-paid women
workers seeking pay equity,
Pakeha against Maori, straight people against q***r and
transgender people.
And this bill serves to pit people with homes and jobs, people with
retail businesses, against the poor, the afflicted, and the
homeless.
Now this kind of populism is not good for our country and for our
people. Not good for our people. I'm ashamed of my government.
You people are the Justice Committee, so please
show some justice, show some humanity, and throw out this
cruel bill, this punitive and actually
unnecessary bill. Thank you. That's my submission.
Thank you very much, Marie. We do have time for one or two questions if any
members wish to ask.
Oh.
Rima Markley.
Hi, Marie. So speaking of compassion and Christian values,
what would you say to the young restaurant owner, it's a new
business for him, in South Auckland that has a young
family and has said to me that because of the
people hanging out in front of his restaurant,
patrons have said, "I'm sorry, I want to support you, but I can't
because I don't feel comfortable walking in with so
many people
outside hanging out outside your restaurant." What do you say to that out of
compassion? Is there no compassion for the restaurant owner?
I will answer your question, but I just wanted to note, I made some notes about
your background, madam. I noted that you noted your background on
crime.
You know about my background. What's the answer to the question?
I will get to it.
What would you say to him?
I note that you're keen on law and order. You've failed miserably.
I'm also keen on helping people in my electorate that come up to me with problems.
You're very keen on boot camps, I understand, and on prisoners and military
academies.
No. I will answer the question.
All right. Thank you both.
Marie,
Rima has asked you a question, so if you don't mind just answering what she's
asked, please.
I will. I would say to that person, ask the people who are in
the way of your business to move.
That's all that's needed. They will move along.
Oh, okay. Because you've been there, done that.
Okay. Thank you very much. Thank you, Marie, for your submission and for your
time. We appreciate you coming before us today. Thank you.
Chair, I just want to address that it's not fair for a committee member to
talk over a submitter and to be aggressive to a submitter.
I do would like the committee members to have some level of
decorum.
That's not aggressive.
Yeah. So-
That is not aggressive
... talking over a submitter is.
No, it's not.
Understood. And thank you, Lawrence.
There is a difference in a manner of talking.
Yeah.
Some decorum is necessary, but also at the same time,
I would note that when members are asked questions or submitters are asked
questions, that they answer or refer to the question that is asked rather
than making personal remarks about different members of the
committee, but in a respectful way and not talking over one another as well.
Okay. We will come to our next submitter, Lisa Lees.
Okay,
I'm reading in the chat that Lisa is saying, "I don't have a microphone.
Can you please phone me?"
So we might come back to Lisa, if that is okay.
I think
if Kitty might be online.
Thank you, Lisa. We can read your messages.
But obviously, we
would love for you to make an oral submission to us.
We appreciate that you can see and hear us, but we need to be able to hear you for
your submission as well.
We're going to jump to Cameron Jenkins from the Tenants Unit.
If we can get Lisa on the phone, then we will come back to her.
But we will jump to Cam from the Tenants Unit.
Tenants Union. I'm sorry.
Hi.
Hi, Cam.
Can you hear me all okay?
We can, and we can see you as well. So you've got
10 minutes, Cam, so we're in your hands.
Um.
Leave some time at the end for questions.
Yeah. I'm taking the submission, as read, and I've been sitting here
listening to some of the other submitters and certainly the previous question
that's been posed to several of the submitters.
I guess for me, the question comes about of
if we're doing this to give police more powers, why aren't the existing measures
that they have around trespass notices to these people sleeping in the
shop front doorways used because I believe you can
trespass someone from a premises, which would have the same effect as to
your move on orders. I'm greatly concerned that
the people who are sleeping rough
are fundamentally the same people who have
insecure to no housing. And I would say that the aggressive
behaviors from those that are sleeping rough are probably also some of the
ones that have high and complex needs around mental health and addictions.
And so I think fundamentally to get them to the point where we have
just Put them in prison because essentially this law allows
them to go to prison,
is costing our system and society far more than maybe standing up
some actual housing support products that some of these
people
may need. And it even begrudges me that this legislation covers from
14 upwards, therefore, what are we going to do with these
14-year-olds, 14 to 17? We might have a
16-year-old who is
out of care or been kicked out of home, sleeping rough, because they do sleep on
the streets rough, and then we're going to put them in juvenile detention
because we're not going to put a 16-year-old in prison.
So I'm very concerned at the
greater end of the punishment. Furthermore, the $2,000 fine,
we're effectively giving people fines who have no ability and
means will pay for it, because let's be honest, if they had the ability and means
to pay for these things, they wouldn't be sleeping rough on the streets in
the first instance. They would be sleeping in accommodation.
So I'm just very concerned that we're going to be fining
people. People are going to be racking up fines with no ability or means of paying
them, and guess what? We'll give them community services or put them in jail for
non-payment of fines. It seems to be a really
odd way of dealing with the problem.
But I would rather use my time to answer questions than to
talk about and detail my submission.
It's very clear from a Tenants Union perspective of where we sit in terms of
how we could provide some better solutions.
Thank you, Cameron. We've got a couple of questions here, one from Camilla Belich.
Thank you. Thanks for your submission.
I see that from your submission, you're from Palmerston North. Is that true?
Yes, yes. Lovely to see you, Camilla.
I just had a question around, we've had quite a few
submissions from people who are based in larger centers like Auckland, and
we've also had a bit of commentary around
rural locations. But I just wanted to know from a smaller
center, what do you think the impact would be if people
were moved on in, say, Palmerston North,
maybe compared to how it would work in other
areas?
We're fortunate that Palmerston North, I think, is
big enough in the sense that we operate as a city, but probably not one of your
larger cities. So we have everything in terms of all the support services
like MSD offices,
other accommodation, stuff around that people could access.
The issue we have is I think from what I see and what my office
sees, is that those who are
sleeping on the streets are either people that are choosing to be there by choice,
or they have complex needs around mental health,
drug and alcohol, that have not been addressed before we get them into stable
housing. So the problem is we're putting them into housing or trying to find
housing solutions for them when we actually haven't addressed or attend to what
is causing them to become homeless to start with.
And so they're in that circle of trying to get
accommodation. No one's accepting them.
We have limited
spaces or places that people can go to when they are at that
high-end need. And once you burn your bridges with those ones, there's nowhere to
go but the street. So then we're either going to put them in jail or we're going to
fine them. And again, we get into that circle of issuing fines to
people who have no means or ability to pay them.
Or at what point are we going to stop moving them on from places and
accept that that place is going to be where they all hang out?
Thank you.
And Dane Rosewarne.
Hey, thanks, Cameron. It's pretty much a supplementary off the back of
Camilla's question, really. You highlight that move on orders don't solve
homelessness, they simply move it elsewhere.
Yep.
Based on the experience of the Tenants Union, what happens to
people when they are moved on without first addressing the
reason that they have nowhere stable to live?
Well, I think we just push the problems somewhere else.
Or if they're fortunate enough, they might be able to go sleep in a
car. They often end up pushing trolleys around
the city with all their belongings.
They might go and sleep in the local domain where it's potentially you can camp out
under a bush because no one's going to worry about you.
So I think what's happened is you're then going to push that urgent need that we
need to address further underground.
And that is a concern, is that you'll have those very
people who probably need more hands-on support going further
underground, which is going to cause more problems on the system,
I think.
Thanks, Cameron.
And a question from Dr. Lawrence Sunan.
Thank you so much, Chair. Thank you for your submission.
And I think I just want to check from your perspective and maybe
either personally or with Tenants Union,
what sort of conversations have you had with
rough sleepers or the homeless community
around this
bill? Because we've just obviously have also heard from submitters
from people who are actually going to be affected by this.
So I don't personally go out on the street and talk to them, but I do work
very closely with--
We were able to get our city council to fund some outreach funding.
So through another provider,
we have dedicated outreach people who go and do have
those conversations with them, and then they feed back in to me about the
needs. And often it's
lack of availability, lack of accommodation that potentially meets
their unique needs,
but it's all because of the needs situation.
I generally believe that everyone we've spoken to have said that they want housing.
If we can get them housing and they stay in housing, the issue
becomes
that we need to separate, that not all beggars
are homeless, and not all homeless people sleeping rough are beggars.
And I think that this bill is trying to capture two things, but they are
two separate, succinct problems and
needs
as well.
Great. Well, I think-
And I'm mindful that we are going to potentially
inadvertently penalize people from either side when that's
not their intention.
Fantastic. Well, thank you, Cameron.
Really appreciate both you presenting to us today, and also your written submission
and the work you do too. So thank you very much.
Fantastic. Thank you for letting me, and I will carry on listening to the other
submitters.
Appreciate your time. Thank you so much, guys. Appreciate it.
No worries. Now, I'm just going to check with the clerks to see whether we have
managed to get hold of Lisa on the phone.
Okay, we're going to bring in Robert.
Going to push him up the queue, and then we'll come back to those that we have
missed. So we'll just bring Robert online.
Hey, Robert.
You've just got yourself on mute.
Are you there, Robert?
Yep, we can see you've got your hand raised, but we cannot hear you.
Okay.
Doesn't look like Robert is going to be an option for us.
Clerks, do we have anybody else online ready to go?
Okay, members, we are just going to suspend for five minutes.
We'll come back online at 2:25, please.
Okay.
Just been following along what's happening. We'll see.
We're going to try and bring Lisa in. I think she's tried to join us by phone.
So we'll see if we can hear you, Lisa.
We can't hear you on the phone, Lisa.
I think the clerk's asking for you to unmute.
Can you hear me now?
We can. Yes, we can.
Yep. Okay, good. Thank you.
Okay, Lisa, while we're on you-
I can see my-
You have five minutes
Oh, five. That's fine
So happy for you to go.
Hang on. Sorry. Yeah, okay.
Yeah, sorry about that. I wasn't really prepared for today.
I didn't realize it was today, so I don't have my submission in front of me.
But it doesn't matter. What I just need to say is...
I'll just turn that off. Sorry.
What I just wanted to say was that shortly I'm probably
going to be homeless, and I'm kind of concerned,
not just for other people as well, but myself also, because I currently
live in a camping ground, and that's not going to be for much
longer. And I don't have anywhere else to go.
So am I going to be ending up in jail or
with some fine or something, because I'm not going to have anywhere to
stay, as WINZ won't even put me into a place anywhere.
So, that's the concern.
Why is it that when there is nowhere else for people to
go,
it doesn't seem right that
we should have to
be subject to a criminal
conviction or a fine just because we don't have anywhere to go.
People, I don't believe, are on the street by choice.
I would have liked to have seen a bill that sort of
would give people who are homeless or who are going to be
homeless the option to have a permanent
residence that they can live in for the rest of their life if they need to.
We just don't have that. Camping grounds here are full of people who are
in similar situations than me. So this is
going to be a concern if they have to move on
from their camping ground, are they going to be homeless as well?
And are we going to see a lot more people in prison or
with fines because we literally don't have anywhere else to go.
Yep, so that's really all I wanted to say.
And then otherwise the rest of my submission, just take that as read. Thank you.
Thank you, Lisa, and we have taken your submission as read.
Just looking to see if any members have any questions.
There's a question from Rima Naklay.
Hi, Lisa. Look, I'm sorry to hear-
Hi
... the position you're in.
I heard you say that MSD won't help you.
I'm happy if you want to reach out to my office-
That's right
... to direct you to your MP so that they can help with MSD.
Because you sound like you're in a situation-
Oh, okay
... where you should be getting help.
So I'm happy for the clerks to give you-
Right
... my email and I'll help you.
Oh, okay. So how do I get your email?
If the clerks can give... Clerks, can you give Lisa my email, please?
We can do that.
All right. Awesome.
Thank you.
Get in touch, Lisa.
Okay. Appreciate that.
Get in touch soon.
Yes.
All right. Bye.
That would be huge. I'll do that. Thank you so much. Thank you for that.
Bye.
Appreciate it. Bye now.
Thank you, Rima. And thank you, Lisa. Appreciate you submitting. All right.
Thank you.
Okay, we're going to see if there's another phone number that's coming up.
See if that is Kitty who was supposed to be submitting with us.
So we'll just see if they can unmute.
Hello.
Hello. Who are we speaking with?
Richard Norvy of the Auckland Community Housing Trust.
All right, Richard. Well, you're here, so we might as well hear your submission.
We thought it might have been somebody else, but hey, we're going to roll with it
anyway. We can be a bit flexible. So Richard, you got 10 minutes.
We've read your submission, but please leave a little bit of time at the end for
some questions members may have.
Sure. Well, I've been
involved with the Auckland Community Housing Trust
since I was its founding chair, and
we dealt initially with
people who'd become homeless because they'd had an acute
episode, and when they went back to their rental accommodation,
it was gone, and similarly, it's often
impossible to return to the family.
Another thing, when I was chair of the Problem Gambling Foundation
for a similar period, there were a number of our clients
who had become homeless because they'd lost all their money, their
relationship had broken, they'd lost their home.
So there's another-- We know that there are people on the
streets because they're addicted to alcohol or drugs,
but there are also some who are there because they're addicted
to various forms of gambling.
And
my wife-- We live in Karangahape
Road. My wife volunteered with the Merge Cafe for the
homeless and heard the stories of the people there.
They're all people who are worthy
of being homed and treated as human beings.
I was
the elected member of the Waiheke-Matata local board who was
on the Karangahape Road Business Association for nine years.
The Karangahape Road businesses have been dealing with this issue.
The Karangahape Road Business Association does not support this
bill. It supports other measures to deal
humanely and long-term productively
with the people on the streets who cause
them and their businesses some issues.
This is not the way that they see it to go.
I'd hoped that
Rose
could have been on. She works for a financial corporate
today, and they didn't give her leave.
But at the end of the week, she works for Kickback,
which works with young homeless people.
And
they're
teenagers who leave home because they find the situation at
that home intolerable,
psychologically or physically.
But they can't get emergency housing because
the government has said that they're people who contribute to their own
homelessness. They've chosen to leave, and
somebody objectively may feel that the situation was not
so bad they had to leave, but from their point of view, they did.
And
we meet 501s
who've been expelled from Australia,
and
they end up
delinked from their family in Australia,
lost and
rough sleepers.
The former Australian Minister of Immigration
talked about taking out the garbage when
he talked about the expulsion of these people.
We now have New Zealand ministers promoting this law
so that
people
on cruise liners don't have to see the rough
sleepers in Auckland.
So they obviously see it as tidying away the garbage
rather than responding to their needs as human
beings and coming up with
long-term housing and support solutions.
And that's what we should be doing at this time.
The government's done a good job at housing people from emergency
housing, but there are some people who their
criteria don't allow them to access it.
There needs to be a restoration of the support
to enable community housing agencies,
Housing New Zealand,
private sector, and community housing providers and iwi
to have the resources to house people rather than this policy.
Thank you.
Thanks, Richard. We've got a couple of people with some questions.
We'll start with Dan Rosewarne.
Hi, Richard. Dan Rosewarne here. You highlight that moving
rough sleepers away from familiar neighborhoods and
connections can intensify things like anxiety,
fear, and alienation. Can you explain why those local
relationships and connections are important for people who
are already vulnerable?
Well, they've lost their familiar housing.
Some of them have come from Northland.
They've lost
their turangawaewae, they've lost connections with their family,
and the particular place in the street where they sleep,
and the particular connections they've made with
other rough sleepers,
and some social workers,
is as close as they've got to a family and a home, and to take that away
really seems appalling.
Thanks, Richard.
And a question from Camilla Belich.
Hi, Richard. Thanks very much for your submission.
I just had a question around something that came up in an earlier
submission, which might be a bit tricky, so hopefully it's one you're
aware of.
Reference to the 2013 bylaw in Auckland, which
allows
people to be moved on by members of the council, and I just
wanted to know if you had any feedback in relation to that
bylaw or any experience with how it operates in practice.
It operates okay, and of course
all the criteria in the current Summary Offences
Act in terms of
genuine antisocial behavior, willful damage,
disorderly, and so on is there.
So it's just that the problem's been allowed to get so big
that there aren't enough police,
and there can't be enough council workers
there at a particular time when the issue arises.
If we're able
to house most of these people,
then the remainder of the more intransigent and difficult people
could, I believe, be handled by the police and council
and social service agencies.
Thank you.
Great. Well, thank you, Richard. Really appreciate both your written and
presenting your submission to us today. Thank you for joining us.
Okay.
Daniel Jackson is our next submitter.
And just to reassure Robert,
Robert, we haven't lost your submission.
You are still in our queue, but we're just coming to Daniel first.
Hey, Daniel. We can see you're online. There we go.
Thank you for joining us. We have read your submission.
You have five minutes. Please do leave a little bit of time at the end for any
questions members may have, but we're in your hands.
Just on you. There we go.
Thank you.
Kia ora koutou.
I'm
a resident of Nelson, and I'm someone who quite
regularly encounters
rough sleepers
out when I'm about, including at night, both in the central
city of Nelson and closer to where I live.
I just want to make the initial comment that the vast
majority of my interactions with
homeless people who are
rough sleepers or who are perhaps
begging for money or who are just
minding their own business have been
pleasant and positive. So I think it's important when we think about
this issue not to start from the
assumption that this is a group of people who are dangerous or a
threat or a problem.
And
when there are particular instances
of,
for example, disorderly or threatening behavior, that's actually something
that's addressed under the current legislation.
So my concern is that we're
essentially here taking an approach where
we're kind of treating a particular group of people as a problem
when it's actually only a small minority of people in
that group who are
exhibiting behaviors that cause a problem.
And even in those cases, you're not actually
addressing the underlying issues here by this.
So I'd say we've got existing powers that can be
used in these cases. If there's a feeling that additional powers are
needed, it should be targeted at the forms of
behavior that are problematic, that are threatening, that are
disorderly, that are causing problems.
And I would argue that the current wording of the
legislation is extremely broad,
quite vague, and imposes significant
limits on human rights under the New Zealand Bill of Rights Act,
whether it's freedom of expression, of which begging is a form,
or whether it's freedom of movement or freedom of assembly.
And
what I would suggest is
if this bill-- I don't think this bill is necessary because this current
law provides for
situations where it's a problem. But if it is to proceed, it needs to be much more
targeted
in addressing the minority of cases
where there are particular behaviors that cause
problems.
Great. Thank you, Daniel. We do have a question from Dr Lawrence Sunan.
Oh, Kia ora. Thank you so much for your submission, Daniel.
Can I again just check on that last bit that you're saying,
one of the Section seven report is around
whether there's a less intrusive way to deal with this.
What are your thoughts in terms of,
I think I believe the term is
less rights intrusive alternative?
Yes. Well, thanks for that question.
I'm a lawyer, and I
did have a look at the Section seven report and also the Law Society submission.
I think that they make good points.
Essentially, the problem is when you have really broad and really
vague
criteria for it, then it's not
the least rights intrusive
measure here. One of the things
the courts look at when is a limit
on a right justified under the Bill of Rights Act is,
does it impair the right no more than is
necessary? And I think here you could craft much more
narrow
criteria for this that address
only cases of really threatening or disruptive
behavior.
And I do think that there are also wider questions about whether these
sort of orders which
don't have a judicial process or anything are also
rights consistent more broadly. But you could certainly frame them in a
narrower way.
And that's something that's necessary in order for something to be a justified
limitation
Fantastic. Well, thank you, Daniel.
Really appreciate both your written and your oral submission today.
So thank you for coming before us and for your work. So thank you.
Okay, we are going to try Robert again.
So Robert, we're just going to promote you, and please just accept the invitation
and make sure you have your camera and your microphone turned off.
Uh, turned on, sorry.
Here we are, Robert. We can hear you.
Hooray.
Happy days. Okay. We have you for five
minutes. We've read your submission, but please do leave a little bit of time at
the end for any questions. Over to you.
Okay. Thank you.
I've heard a lot of the submissions today, and I must
commend you guys for sitting there and listening to all these things.
So well done.
I guess I would be one of the rare few who kind of support
the bill, but I do have a few concerns.
The
origins of this, if I'm correct, come from the Safe
Street bill.
I found the Safe Street bill to be quite detailed into
what it was actually asking for, and
the Move On
bill that we have here,
kind of vague.
It does
present issues when,
say, police are going to issue a move on order,
they take the details of those people that they are going to
confront. And I think that
compared to Australia, because I actually speak at Perth.
Compared from Australia, everything's all verbal
and nothing's taken down as to the
person's identity, et cetera. So that's one of my
main issues.
The other thing is it is totally left up to the
constable, policeman who's issuing these things.
So,
and you get as bad as what it has done over
here in Australia, in that move on orders is just a generic default
where people minding their own business gets pushed along the streets
and stuff like that. But nonetheless, I do
understand where all the shop owners are coming from.
My daughter still stays in Auckland, and she has
said that there have been
beggars, homeless who are waiting by the ATM machines and things like that.
So like a lot of Aucklanders,
they would never, ever go near that ATM. They'll go to another one.
And straight away it ticks a box for
harassment,
fearing for, well, whatever it is you fear
when it comes to
being in contact with these people.
And it's really sad.
They've gotten there because
of circumstances in their life. I think
homeless people
go hand in hand with deteriorating mental health. It really does.
It's got to affect you
when you've been sleeping rough and you develop
life skills, survival skills. So
when you do sleep at night, you don't sleep, and you stay awake because you're
always worried about what's coming around the corner. You sleep during the day.
So I've had a look at
my submission, and I basically wanted
some sort of end game, some sort of resolution for these
homeless
people that we have around the Auckland CBD.
And so I've
touched on, say, a dream where
there's something that we could use, the
vacant land in the Auckland CBD that's just been sitting there for
decades. And a couple of them are car parks, some of them are St.
James and things like that. Why aren't we using that?
And the new ones just
popped up. I think it's the,
yeah, Auckland Police Central.
Now we can develop that into something like a rest
and respite center. The model that I dreamt
up, we small hours, was a modular
container type
effort. And if you read the submission, you have looked through it.
Now that was just a throw it together mismatch, but it's there to
promote
thought.
Why don't we have another look at these areas?
Wilson's car park, they've made enough money. The CRL is coming in soon.
You don't want cars in the city. Let's do something for the
community of the CBD and for homeless sleepers right now,
and
get a facility open. You can have a couple of them in the city
where rough sleepers can just come in for the night, have a safe place to
sleep. And I think I just about covered everything
that I want to cover. If there are any questions here, fire away.
But thanks for
reaching back out to me. I thought I'd lost you. Cheers.
Fantastic. Well, thank you, Robert. We have reached your five-minute allocation.
But we do thank you very much for your submissions and also for your patience
and getting to your submission as well.
So thank you very much for joining us this afternoon.
Okay, we are going to go to Garth and
Elizabeth
My apologies, actually, we were going to be going to Peter Lynham. Sorry, Peter.
We were coming to you. I completely forgot that we had had that message.
So Peter, if you could just switch on your camera and
unmute yourself.
There we go. You've got five minutes.
We have read your submission, Peter, but if you leave a little bit of time at the
end for any questions members may have. We're in your hands.
Yes.
Now, I'm a historian, retired from Massey University,
and so I thought it would be helpful to comment on the longer term
perspective. That there's been a long tradition in New
Zealand of rough sleeping and begging.
19th century New Zealand was full of such people.
And in the Depression years, I wrote a history,
for the centenary of the Auckland City Mission, and
it's very interesting that in the Depression years, the provision of
a doss house for the single male poor
became a crucial part that built up the Auckland City
Mission into its current enterprise.
And in recent years, the City Mission, along
with the Methodist Mission and some other social agencies,
were involved with the city council in running a night shelter,
but had to close it down because of the withdrawal of financial
support, and because of the sheer problems of needing
multiple people to maintain it.
Now, what we have seen, and I give figures in my book, of
2004, primary homeless were
64. 2014, it had risen to
147, and then
by 2018, there
were
336 chronically homeless people in
Auckland. I think that context needs to be remembered.
And of course, it's replicated in other cities, and important to remember, it's
replicated throughout the Western world.
Now,
as I've explained in my submission, and as I see has been
endorsed by the Attorney General's advice,
there is
obviously concern about the broadness of the statements
about rough sleeping and about begging.
But you'll be aware of their advice, and I'm sure you will take that seriously.
I am well aware because, as you'll hear
later when I come on along with somebody else from the Auckland Rainbow
Community Church to comment,
the problems of
violence in some of the homeless people can be
very confronting. But I would note, in
particular, that a lot of rough sleeping is forced
on people. I do work in supporting people from prison,
and in my submission, I discuss the ways in which people
who have left prison are often faced with almost
impossible circumstances. One I dealt with
who ended up on the streets in Pukekohe.
There was just nothing available until
his ex-partner gave him the children to care for,
and then
a house was provided for him. So my concern
is that this measure does not in fact
provide tools that will be helpful, and at the same
time, places and makes more vulnerable many other
homeless people.
Fantastic. Well, thank you very much, Peter, and I'll just see if any members have
a question for you.
Dr Lawrence Sunam.
No, Rima had her hand up first.
Okay. Thank you, Doctor.
Rima Machlei.
Thanks, Doctor. So can I just ask, so
I appreciate your concern about is something like
this going to make homelessness even worse, even though the
priority is about some safety around businesses.
But have you not heard the comments made by the ministers
that when police are moving people on, they need to
direct them to services that will help with
the conditions that come, oftentimes mental health conditions,
with a lot of our homeless? Have you heard that and-
Yes
... yeah, that call at all?
Yes, I have heard that, and
with the greatest of respect, those services, for example, the
Auckland City Mission and Lifewise, Methodist
Mission Northern, which are the ones that operate mostly in the central area,
have really nothing to offer. The process which has been
developed in their program to place people into
accommodation involves a step-by-step process because it's
very difficult to move from being on the streets to being a
stable resident. And so what they have developed is stage
one, you're admitted into James Liston House, et
cetera, until gradually you're admitted into more regular
accommodation. And the problem is, James Liston House
has a total occupancy, it's 58 people it can take.
That just simply cannot meet the needs. It's not a night shelter.
Thank you.
Fantastic. Well, thank you, Peter.
We've met our allocated five minutes, but we thank you for your patience
and for submitting with us, and I suspect we will be hearing from you again soon.
So thank you.
Thank you.
Now we'll move to, let's just have a look, Garth and
Elizabeth.
Hi, Garth.
We can see that you have unmuted.
We have you down for five minutes. We have read your submission, so if you just
leave a little bit of time at the end for any members to ask a question, but we're
entirely in your hands.
You've just muted yourself, Garth.
Garth, if you can hear us, you have muted yourself, so we cannot hear you
if you are speaking.
Hello, Garth.
Okay. What I think we will do is, I'm not sure what's going
on at Garth's end, but I can see that
Brenda Lowe Johnson is online and available.
So I think we will jump to her, and then see if we can get Garth back online,
if that's okay, please.
Hi, Brenda.
Brenda, if you can hear us, you have yourself muted as well, if you're able to
unmute.
There we go.
Can you hear me?
We can. Fantastic. Brenda, we have you down for five minutes.
Okay.
We have read your submission, and if you just leave a little bit of time at the
end, we may have some questions for you. But over to you.
Okay. Thank you. I oppose this bill in its entirety and
respectfully request that it be withdrawn from the legislative
process.
My name is Brenda Lowe Johnson, and I'm founder of the Homeless
Collective in Christchurch. For approximately 15 years,
I worked alongside people experiencing homelessness,
supporting some of our most vulnerable community members with dignity,
respect, and practical solutions.
During that time, our collective was not government funded.
We had to find our own ways to sustain our work because we were not taken on
board by government agencies, despite achieving
significant outcomes.
Through our collective efforts, we helped more than 1,000 people
into housing and supported approximately 300
real people
into employment. Those numbers represented real
people, real whanau, and real lives that were
transformed when someone took the time to listen,
to care, and provide meaningful support.
It is from this experience that I strongly oppose the Summary
Offences Move on Orders Amendment Bill.
This bill approaches homelessness, poverty, and
vulnerability through a lens of enforcement rather than support.
It risks treating people who are already struggling
as though they are the problem, when in reality they are often the victims of
systemic failures. People
experiencing homelessness are not criminals
because they are poor. They are not criminals
because they have nowhere to go. They are not criminals because they have fallen
through gaps in housing, mental health, addiction,
employment, or social support systems.
The answer is not to move people on.
The answer is to move people into housing, support employment and
stability. My experience has shown that this can be
achieved without stripping people of their mana, dignity, or
human rights. The people I worked with wanted opportunities.
They wanted to contribute. They wanted a pathway forward.
Many had experienced years of broken promises from organizations
and agencies that had told them help was on their way, but nothing
was changed.
I first saw hand the generosity and resilience of people
experiencing homelessness. Following the earthquakes in
Christchurch, many people who were homeless stepped up to help
others. Some assisted in rescue and recovery efforts.
They supported fellow community members during a time of crisis.
Their contributions often went unrecognized, despite demonstrating the
very best of human compassion and community support
spirit. This bill fails to recognize that
humanity. Instead, it risks further marginalizing people
who are already vulnerable.
I struggle to understand the logic of issuing fines or enforcement
measures against people who often have no financial means to pay
them. Such approaches do not solve homelessness.
They do not improve wellbeing. They do not create housing.
They do not connect people to employment.
They simply create additional barriers and deepen existing
hardship. If Parliament genuinely wishes to address
homelessness, it should invest in evidence-based
solutions that work. It should ensure that the right organizations and
people are funded and supported to provide housing, wraparound
service, employment pathways, mental health
support, addiction services, and long-term case management.
There must be proper assessment of individual needs,
meaningful monitoring of outcomes, and accountability for
services receiving public funding.
Success should be measured by how many people are housed,
supported, and empowered by,
not how many people are moved from one location to the other.
The people I worked alongside taught me that everyone deserves dignity,
respect, and hope They deserve to be seen as human beings first.
This bill does not hold those values.
For these reasons, I oppose the Summary Offences Move
On Orders Amendment Bill in its entirety and
urge the
committee to recommend that it be withdrawn.
If kindness is sown,
then kindness you shall receive.
Fantastic, Brenda. Hey, thank you so much for joining us this afternoon
and for both your written and your oral submission.
We have reached your five-minute allocated time.
So thank you very much for joining us this afternoon. We do appreciate it.
Thank you.
We're going to try Garth and Elizabeth again,
see if we can reconnect with them, and hopefully we'll be able to hear them this
time.
All right, Garth, if you can hear us, we would love it if you would unmute, and
then we can hear your oral submission.
Are you there, Garth?
Kia ora koutou.
We can hear you. Fantastic. You have five minutes. We've read your submission.
Please do leave time at the end for any questions.
Kia ora koutou, busy people on the Justice Committee.
Warm thanks for letting us come in from our own living room.
Garth and Elizabeth are in the 85 plus age group.
We're living safely and warmly in our own home.
And today, Tiki Vaekosa is here in support.
We've set out our reasons for submitting.
We're passionate about this nation,
treaty-based,
and becoming more and more multi-ethnic.
We collectively are learning to be inclusive
and compassionate.
We're enthusiastic about the partnerships
between government
and social service agencies.
We're enjoying the new cultural skills of our police.
They're using it to keep every one of us
safe.
We're opposed to this bill
because it undermined good things that government
and police
and social services
are already doing,
and it does not protect and keep safe
people who are vulnerable and already at risk,
those who are homeless,
and those who are sleeping rough.
It gives a new task to the police,
which is counter
to keeping all of us safe and protected.
All people who are homeless,
at risk of becoming victims of crime,
physical attacks,
theft of belongings,
rape,
and even murder.
Teenagers,
the elderly,
the differently abled,
women
who are sleeping rough
are victims far too often.
We ask that this bill be withdrawn.
We ask this committee and all other political parties
to stop the bill from proceeding.
But if you do proceed with the bill,
we ask that two specific recommendations be
inserted for teenagers, for women,
and for elderly.
Two examples.
Before police issue move on orders to teenagers,
they should be required
to make links to an appropriate youth service.
And the second one is that people under the
age of 16 should be exempted from
move on orders. Kia ora koutou.
Fantastic. Thank you, Garth, and appreciate your patience while we got there.
I'll just see if any members of the committee have a question for you. Carl Bates.
Thanks very much, Chair, and thanks, Garth, for your
presentation or submission to the committee.
On your point about the referral to the appropriate service,
do you think it would be appropriate if the move on order required
someone to move on to one of those services?
Otherwise, the offense would then come into play.
Is that essentially what you're saying?
This is giving the police the ability or should give the police the
ability to direct the individual to the appropriate service,
and then if they weren't to take that up, would it be appropriate for the offense
to stand?
I think the police are good at relating to social services or youth
services, and I think they should be allowed to do that
rather than issue move on orders.
And so I suppose my question is, if the person then wasn't
willing to take up that advice or that connection or wouldn't work with
police in doing that, is it then appropriate for police to take that
next step in their judgment?
I trust the police and I trust the social services to handle that
situation.
Okay. Thank you.
Fantastic. Well, thank you, Garth.
Really appreciate you joining us this afternoon and for making a written
submission on the bill as well, and thank you for your time
Okay. We will come to Ellen. Ellen Blake.
Hey, Ellen. Thank you for joining us this afternoon.
We have read your submission.
We have you down for five minutes, if you can leave a little bit of time for
questions at the end. Thank you.
Thank you. Kia ora tātou.
Thank you for the opportunity to speak.
I've just come in from working outside, so I'm all rugged up because it's
very chilly here. I live in a nice, warm, dry home in central
Wellington. So I see people sleeping rough on our footpaths
often.
I don't think there's any need at all for a move on orders bill, and certainly
not to fine people who have no money.
I think I would like the committee to please withdraw this bill.
I think the police have enough powers now, and they don't need
any more to do the job that they do under trying circumstances
already. And I would really dearly like to see the police focus their resources on
more important and significant issues, like domestic violence.
Now I'm old enough to remember,
and to know that sleeping on footpaths and in cars is not a
normal activity, and it's not right, and it affects all of us
in our community. Nobody likes it, and people certainly don't
choose to do that.
Move on orders won't address the issues of homelessness.
In Wellington, we've got over 640 households still on our housing
waiting list.
They need government to build more homes so that they can have somewhere to live.
And we need that to be properly funded and for all politicians to please
support building enough homes for people.
And please also fund
the services that we have. We have a very excellent service in Wellington Downtown
Community Ministry, which I think you're hearing from later.
And they go and help people to shift from
living rough into a much more
better circumstances where they can achieve more with their life.
So please fund more houses and
services that support people who are in need.
Thank you. That's all I've got to say.
Fantastic. Thank you, Ellen. I will look to see if any members have a question for
you.
There don't appear to be any. We-- Oh, Dr Laurence Yuen.
Cool. Thank you so much. Thank you so much for your submission, Ellen.
And I think this is something that is, again, a reoccurring
theme and line of questioning when we have other submitters as well.
And I think in your role here in your local communities, the question
is
where would the people be moved on to, being one of the questions.
And then the follow-up question for that would be
in terms of, again, your area and your region, what
24/7 support networks are there if police should refer to them
to other places? Because, again, police might be doing that already, but what
happens if for some it closes at 5:00 PM?
Yeah. We did have a night shelter, but that's got changed
into Wellington City Mission,
more long-term trying to help people off the streets.
And we have other great services like
Wellington City Mission that have a new place up towards
Newtown and things like that, but there just simply isn't enough places.
There's 640 households on an urgent waiting list.
They've been sat there for some time. There isn't enough places for people to go.
There isn't enough emergency and transitional support.
There isn't enough people who, like Downtown Community Ministry, who go onto
the streets and help people find new
places and new homes. There just isn't enough.
And I think we need to be
optimistic. We can address this. We helped people off the
street during COVID times. We can do better than we are doing
now.
Fantastic. Well, thank you, Ellen.
Really appreciate you coming inside, rugging up warm for us, and
presenting to us this afternoon. So thank you very much for your time.
Thank you.
Fantastic. We're going to go now to Dale Marie Morgan.
And just want to say thank you, Dale
Marie, for your patience
while we got to you as well. Over to you. You have five minutes.
Leave a little bit of time at the end for questions.
Tēnā koe, Tom, and you're doing a great job at chairing, even when some of
us are a little bit technically challenged on our side.
So ka nui te mihi ki a koutou, tenei
komiti. And thank you for the opportunity to speak to you
guys today. So of course, I'll just put my personal
declaration, this is a personal one and not my elected member
hat on today.
I'd like to bring up a couple of points that
I'd just like to raise on top of my submission, and it's around some of the
funding.
Because I believe I am opposing this
bill
because I think when we look at the frontline policing, what they got
allocated this year, 391 million, I think.
512 million to corrections, 224 million to
justice. That's one billion forty-eight million.
And we can't find money to
support some of the services that Ellen and those that have
presented before me have
spoken about such the great work of our support
services on the ground that do so much for our people.
And I know most of us that are sitting here in this space today,
we all get to go home to a home where it's warm, and we have
warm sheets, and we have a warm home And
right now, underneath Matariki in Puanga, this
is the coldest part of our year.
And tenui te mihi ki a koe Dr. Sunam, because you have
pointed out the obvious. If they get moved on after 5:00,
what happens then?
E mihi ana ka koe to korerorima. I
heard what you said, but I do have to say the ministers aren't listening
to us. I hear what the korero is, engari au i te
whakae i te korero i te minita
o te Minita Whanake
Maori. Kari ia i whakarongo i a matou.
He nui nga Maori i runga i te rori.
Nui nga Maori i houseless.
Maori are not homeless, we're houseless because this is our home.
We have no other home. Ko Aotearoa ta tatou kainga.
And we all know that if everyone had a home
or more people had homes, we'd have fewer costs at A&E with
them presenting, and we'd also have fewer costs that
are attributed to poverty and crime.
So
I know that your guys' schedule is behind today, so I'm not going to hold you up
too much, and I just am very grateful for the time to speak to this.
Kia ora koutou.
Thanks, Dale Marie.
Really appreciate your submission to us.
I will just see if any members have a question for you.
Don't appear to be any, but we really appreciate your patience and understanding
while we tried to catch up a little bit on our schedule, and thank you very much
for your written and oral submission as well.
Tena koutou. Thank you.
Have a good afternoon. Thank you.
Members, I'm just going to give us a brief five-minute break.
We were scheduled to have it a few minutes ago, just to give you an opportunity if
you need to, and we will just come back online at 3:20, please.
All righty. Welcome back members, and thank you, Aaron, for your
patience. Appreciate you waiting for us.
Aaron, we have you down for 10 minutes on behalf of the Housing
Alliance Otago. We've read your submission,
and please do leave a bit of time at the end for questions. Over to you.
Tena koe, Mr. Chairman. Tena tatou katoa.
Opportunity to share some thoughts with you this afternoon.
I'm sure I'm not the only person you've dealt with today who's also running the
school holidays gauntlet.
So apologies in advance for any unscheduled feedback you may
receive from this end. It is, as the previous
submitter
noted, also Pouaka Matariki, and
a great opportunity for us all to reflect on
what we want a society to look like and what we want this country to look like.
And of all the things, I guess, I thank
the legislation at hand, the bill at hand for offering us
that opportunity.
Imagine a world where we all have somewhere warm,
dry, and safe to call home. Where
new homes are built to a standard that keeps us all healthy, and
our existing ones have either been retrofitted or redeveloped.
Where renting for life is a dignified option for people, but
private landlords are the exception rather than the rule.
Where our communities are empowered to support each other, and our elders are able
to live rich and active lives close to their families and friends.
Where our towns and cities are designed to adapt to our changing
climate, and to foster human connection.
Where the aspirations of mana whenua to provide for their people are enabled at
all levels of government.
A world where all of these efforts
are able to be more than the sum of their parts, thanks to local
leadership and backed by government.
The good news is that we know what works.
The bad news is that we still seem to be picking the things that
don't. Whanau experiencing homelessness are
at the most acute end of housing need in this country.
Housing First or the Housing First model has shown what's possible
when you do the simple things well.
Build more houses for people to live in,
and then provide the support that they need to stay there and
live stable lives. The approach being taken by this
bill, unfortunately, is almost the exact opposite of
this.
It is simplistic, it's unworkable, and it's unnecessary,
and you don't have to take my word for it.
That's the feedback that's been provided by officials all the way through as this
legislation has been developed. Local councils and the
police in particular, have provided very clear
feedback along these lines. So what can we
make then of the decision to ignore all of this advice
and plow on regardless? To proceed with
legislation that you have been told will adversely affect some
of our most vulnerable people.
Housing Alliance Otago is a collective impact network working
across the Otago region to improve housing outcomes.
A region where
there aren't enough homeless people, we're told,
to
get the support that is being made available in other parts of the country.
Support which doesn't travel any further south than the Waimakariri
District. Expansion of these supports, the likes of which we've seen
recently from the government should be applauded, but it is
not
the case that they would mitigate the harm that this legislation would cause.
We are committed to the goal of ending homelessness in Otago,
as should be our goal for the entire country.
This is important because now more than
ever before, a range of other policy decisions are being taken that
will knowingly increase the number of our whanau in this situation.
These include, but are not limited to, changes to the Residential
Tenancies Act, which bring back no-cause evictions, massive
scaling back of the Kainga Ora New Build program,
changes to social welfare making teenaged adults no longer eligible
for job seeker support, and attempts to enshrine the
conservative culture wars in statute with a binary definition
of gender, potentially forcing our trans and
non-binary communities to effectively disavow their gender
identities in order to access the public services that they are
entitled to. All of these decisions were taken knowing that they
would make the situation worse for those at the most acute end
of housing need. So when we consider this proposed legislation
within the context of the wider legislative program,
there's only one conclusion we can come to.
The proposed legislation isn't remotely interested in improving the
lives of people with the least to lose.
It's an act of performative cruelty to appease
certain voices within the retail lobby, and I put it to the committee that it will
improve the lives of exactly nobody.
In both of my previous roles working in local government
And working in resource management, I've been a staunch advocate for the
importance of our city and suburban centers to wider community wellbeing.
They need to be welcoming and accessible places for all of us.
But they're also, by their very nature, noisy and contested
environments. On any given day, there may be a number of activities in our city
centers that individuals may find confronting or
objectionable. Among them I would include buskers,
commission-driven charity fundraisers, preachers, street appeal
collectors,
and yes, beggars and rough sleepers.
Only the last two of which are singled out by this bill, which
amounts to an effort
to criminalize poverty. And as I've said
before, and it's said in our written submission, entirely unnecessary given the
powers that are already available to police to deal with
safety,
antisocial behavior, and other
more disruptive elements.
Kia ora tatou.
Thanks, Aaron. We do have a couple of people with questions.
We'll start with Dan Rosewarne.
Hey, thanks for that submission, Aaron.
Having served as the mayor of Dunedin, and as a councilor before that,
you've dealt firsthand with the concerns about city
center safety and accessibility, and I was just
wondering from your experience, what approaches have been most
effective in addressing homelessness and supporting
vibrant city centers? You kind of half answered the question earlier, but I just
wanted to flesh that out a little bit more.
Yeah, thanks, Dan. What works is building people houses and putting
them in them, and then providing the supports for people to be able to maintain
that. I can't speak too much to
government programs that are in place to support this because they're not
available here. We would love for the support that is available in other
places to be available in Dunedin and across Otago, and this
certainly isn't just a Dunedin issue.
You go to any district in the country, from the largest metropolitan center to the
smallest rural and provincial council, and they will tell you that this is--
In some ways it's even more challenging in the smaller areas because they don't
have the same sorts of infrastructure, both in the community sector
or in the public sector, as we do. But,
that's what we know works, and that's what we should be getting on with doing
as opposed to wasting everybody's time with this process.
Thanks, Aaron.
And a question from Dr Lawrence Sunan.
Kia ora. Thank you so much for your submission, Aaron.
You've laid out the recommendation really clearly, but actually we'd be more keen
to know from your observation based on
Ōpōtiki,
what has been some of the trends in terms of homelessness
and rough sleeping in your local area? Has it increased?
Do you see
changes in demographics?
Because we've heard from Housing First Ōtautahi that there is a
significant increase in the number of seniors.
Yeah.
That wouldn't surprise me. One of the more frustrating things
is that we don't have an accurate enough picture.
We can infer things from census data for as long as that
exists,
but the
expression of homelessness as it relates to
rough sleeping and begging is a fairly small percentage of
an overall population. And
nothing that we are seeing would challenge what the Christchurch
experience has been around
one of the fastest growing cohorts of people who are experiencing homelessness are
older women. It makes sense when you think about people who are finally in a
situation where they're able to extricate themselves from
relationships. The support services at the community level are
also under strain, and we're seeing that around the
country as not-for-profits who are set up to support survivors
of sexual violence or domestic violence
are struggling. And we see
a government largely standing idly by and
watching them crack under the strain, and I think that's what we mean
when we talk about building up the supports at a community level,
and building up the housing stock for people to live in.
And that's what we need to be getting on with doing.
But yeah, it's a far more complicated picture than you might
see walking down George Street on any given day.
Fantastic. Well, thank you very much, Aaron. That's our 10 minutes with you.
No interruptions from any kids from the school holidays, but thank you very
much for your submissions with us today.
We really appreciate you being with us.
Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
Okay. We're now going to come to Downtown Community Ministry Charitable Trust,
and Natalia, I think we-- There you
are. Fantastic. Well, we've got you
for 10 minutes.
Please do leave a little bit of time at the end for any questions members may have.
Yep. Kia ora. Tēnā koutou katoa. My name's Natalia Cleland.
I'm the Manahoutū or CEO at Downtown Community Ministry,
DCM in Wellington.
One of the things people in my profession sometimes forget is that
not everyone sees the realities of homelessness in the way that we do.
When you work in the sector day after day, year after year, you come to
understand the complexity, the causes, and the likely consequences of
policy decisions. I'm not a politician.
I've taken university papers in public policy, spent time with politicians,
worked with legislation throughout my social work career, followed parliamentary
processes, but I do not claim to be an expert in politics or
lawmaking. I'm here today as an expert in homelessness.
I stand alongside many others who have appeared before this committee already
today, and will continue to appear over the week.
Academics, social workers, leaders of community organizations like my own
People who have dedicated their careers to understanding the causes of poverty,
marginalization, and homelessness, and are finding ways to
meaningfully and effectively address these things.
I'm certain that the common theme that you'll hear from us as experts who are
opposing this bill is, as currently drafted, the bill will criminalize
people who are experiencing homelessness.
The intention may be public order, but the practical effect will be
something quite different. I've seen similar consequences from measures
that appear neutral on the surface.
For example, liquor bans are intended to address public
disorder, yet in practice, for people who are
often caught up in the enforcement are those experiencing addiction and
homelessness. So rather than addressing the underlying issue,
these measures frequently result in fines and repeated
interactions with police for people whose behavior may not be
causing harm to others at that time.
Move on orders risk operating in the same way.
Police will be placed in a difficult position of enforcing law against people
who often have nowhere else to go. A person may refuse to move because there's
literally no other option available to them, or they may
comply, move elsewhere, and be asked to move on again.
The legislation will increase contact between some of our most vulnerable
citizens and the justice system.
At the same time that this bill is being considered, nearly 20,000
households, and it's ironic that they're called households, remain
on the social housing register. These are not individuals.
This is a group of people. And MSD themselves have
assessed over 18,000 of these as at, and
I quote, "At risk with severe and persistent housing needs
that must be addressed immediately," yet suitable housing is
not simply available.
The law should not punish people for circumstances they have no realistic ability
to change. Compliance requires opportunity.
When the lawful option does not exist, when there is no housing for people to
move on to, enforcement ceases to be about behavior and
instead becomes punishment for poverty.
To use a simple analogy, it would be like fining someone for not obtaining a
warrant of fitness on their car when there's no inspection centers available for
them to access.
Now I want to address the matter of rough sleeping in public places.
People generally do not sleep in public because it's more comfortable, or because
they are intentionally trying to be a bother.
They sleep there because it's safer than the alternatives.
For many rough sleepers, particularly women, high visibility
locations offer protection. There are CCTV cameras,
passing members of the public, lighting, witnesses.
The alternatives are often hidden locations where violence, assault,
theft, and sexual victimization are more likely to occur.
CPTED, the Crime Prevention Through Environmental Design, is used
to assess how physical environments influence crime and safety.
One of the consistent findings is that dark, isolated
places with poor lighting and limited visibility
create opportunities for crime because there are fewer people around to see what's
happening.
I understand that seeing people sleeping rough can be
uncomfortable, but I believe that most New Zealanders would rather
experience discomfort than see a person put into a position when they're
more at risk of harm.
When we examine why people become homeless, the causes are remarkably
consistent. As with DCM's data, which you will have seen in my
submission,
HUD's homelessness, or the new HUD, Homelessness
Insight Report, also identifies factors such as
affordable housing,
financial hardship, mental distress, addiction, family violence,
relationship breakdown, as well as people leaving prisons, hospitals,
and state care without stable housing.
What is notably absent from that list is personal preference.
People are not choosing homelessness.
It's an outcome of multiple system failures colliding in a person's life.
So finally, I ask you to consider where public money is best
spent. We know it costs taxpayers around $3,000 a
week to keep people in remand on custody, compared to around
$550 a week for a social housing property.
New Zealand and international evidence tells us that housing people reduces
costs across the health, justice, and social welfare
systems, while delivering substantive economic returns.
As a country, we need to make a decision.
Do we continue forking out billions to keep people homeless, or should we spend
a lot less and end it for the betterment of all New Zealanders?
My colleagues and I do not condone violence, intimidation, or harmful behavior.
When offenses occur, people should be held accountable.
But this bill goes further than addressing harmful conduct.
It risks imposing additional penalties on people who are already living with the
effects of poverty, trauma, mental illness, addiction, disability, brain
injury, and housing exclusion, and these problems can't be enforced
away. I began by saying that I'm not an expert in politics.
Equally, and with respect, I do not think that members of this committee would
claim to be experts in homelessness.
The expertise sits with the people who work in this space every day, and
those who experience homelessness themselves.
Those of us in this field are telling you that this bill,
based on our experience and evidence, will create greater harm and impose
greater costs for the taxpayers.
Over the course of the day, you've heard from experts, Gill Hawkey from
Christchurch Methodist Mission, Professor Neville Pearce from
Otago, leaders at Lifewise Trust, and so
on, and we're all saying the same thing despite coming from different
organizations and different perspectives.
We're telling you that this bill, as currently drafted, will increase
criminalization of homelessness and create further harm for people who
already have the fewest options
and are living on the margins. So we strongly urge this committee to recommend
against the bill in its current form. Thank you for your time.
Thank you very much. We've got a question from Dan Rosewarne.
Thanks for that submission. You highlight that it's not
uncommon for people to be discharged from prison or
hospital directly into homelessness.
Can you explain how often you see that happen?
Yeah.
And what it tells us about the system's response to homelessness.
Yeah. In the submission, I really wanted to pull that out because I don't think
that that's really well known. We probably get
maybe two people a week that come through our small NGO.
We're a really small NGO.
Wow.
None of you will have even heard of us, right?
We're not the big city missions, and we would get two a week, including
501 deportees, and people often being discharged
from remand from prison, both sentenced and on remand,
into homelessness.
Thanks, Natalia.
And Camilla Belich.
Thanks, Natalia, and I have heard of the Downtown Community Ministry, so
thanks for your work. Sorry my voice has suddenly got a bit croaky asking all these
questions today. But I just wanted to ask you, you talked about
the unintended effects of this bill.
Do you think that there is going to be, potentially if this bill was implemented,
an issue around social acceptance of the move on order?
So what I mean is
the kind of the community response to
the approach of
essentially empowering police officers to
put in place these move on orders, and the impact of that.
It's just kind of thinking through the-
Yeah
... options for
It's been a-
... making things worse for-
It's a real concern for us because I think that it's the same
with the liquor ban. That's why I made that point, that if the public see the
police walking past someone who has a bottle, but they're causing
no harm, there's going to be problems for the police in
terms of their reputation for not doing something that was expected of them.
And I really feel, you heard a speaker sort of five speakers
ago who talked about, "I really trust the police judgment here." I do think that
the police know the people, and they know their stories, and they know
the circumstances that that person's in.
We really want to empower the police to be able to make those decisions, and I
think there will be public pressure from them.
They will not be able to walk past someone who they know for certain
isn't causing a problem and doesn't have anywhere to go.
They can't walk past them, I don't think, without the public
making a problem with that.
Fantastic. Well, thank you so much
for your time, and for your submission, and for joining us.
We really do appreciate it. And thank you for your patience as well.
Thank you.
All right. We're going to come to Vic Labor with Charlie and Sophie.
Hopefully they're ... There we are. They're both there. Great.
Thank you both for joining us. You've got 10 minutes for your submission.
Please do leave a little bit of time at the end for questions.
Yeah. Kia ora koutou. My name is Charlie. I'm the Maori vice chair.
I'm here with Sophie, our policy and campaigns officer.
Vic Labor is the youth branch of the Labor Party here in Te Whanganui-a-Tara.
We just want to thank the committee members so very much for giving us the
opportunity to speak on this bill.
Yeah. And so
we're here to strongly oppose this bill.
Sophie will be speaking to the problems and kind of the backwards morality
with this bill, and I'll be speaking to recommendations and kind of an
alternative approach for the homelessness crisis that we hope the committee
consider before closing.
So this bill has made me and some of my other fellow students reflect on our
personal experiences with homelessness, especially in Wellington.
I can confidently say that neither myself or any other student has ever looked at a
person sleeping rough or being on the street and thought that they should be fined
or go to prison just for that.
My experience and the general experience of many of the people I've spoken to is
that homeless people are not often intimidating or
scary on any personal level at all.
They are, at least in our experience for the most part, simply existing.
I have spent some time doing volunteer work in the city center for an organization
called Take 10, which works on Friday and Saturday nights looking after
people between the hours of 10:00 PM and 3:00 AM.
Having spent some time with and around homeless people, and that it is
staggering the level of deprivation and misery that these people are experiencing,
especially given that services are often
not available on weekends or that late at night.
They come to us and I hear a lot of their stories, and it is
pretty harrowing. And they are not in our city centers just because they want to
be. They are there because they do not have another option.
Many of which are dealing with addiction issues, trauma, severe mental health
issues, and I do believe that that would be made actively worse by dealing with
fines, arrests, or imprisonments.
Many people do feel uncomfortable seeing homeless people.
I don't think any of this is pretending as though they don't.
And it should make you uncomfortable to see somebody having to
sleep on the floor outside in the cold.
That should make you uncomfortable.
But what we do with that feeling of uncomfortableness is what really matters
here, and
it is frankly embarrassing that this has continued to worsen the way that it is.
And I think that our feelings towards it, our feeling of embarrassment and shame
surrounding seeing homeless people should not be harnessed to
push them away. I think it should be used as a motivation to do better
work as a better state that does not fail these individuals.
Charlie?
Yeah. So yeah, as I said, I'll be speaking to the recommendations.
So as a whole, we recommend that this bill not proceed, but
if it is of the view
of the committee that this bill do proceed,
we do recommend that the bill be amended to create clarity about what is and
isn't considered disorderly behavior.
What qualities makes a person disorderly?
Is an officer meant to make their own interpretation on the day as to what
this behavior is considered?
And secondly, pair the implication of these move on orders
to greater funding for welfare services.
And so one
kind of a core way of doing this is by creating a duty to assist
legislative framework that creates a legal
obligation for the government to prevent and relieve homelessness.
That is by having initiatives for government agencies across
both central and local government
that aim to address the systemic issues that prevent people from getting support
when they need it. Now, we won't be the first country to do this.
This is common overseas. If you look at Wales over in the
United Kingdom,
they mandate local authorities to help people when they recognize that there's a
likelihood that they're going to be homeless within the next 56 days.
So it's preventative, it's preventing people going onto the streets.
Also recognizing if their current stay is temporary, if they have to
move because of violence or threats, and a range of other criteria that ensures
that people don't resort to the streets as a last option.
And when they recognize that, they provide emergency accommodation and
other support to transition back into permanent housing.
So if we're to implement something like this in New Zealand, this will
subsequently result in greater funding for Housing First, an
existing program that funds community
providers.
Kind of an
area to start, I guess, is removing the 12-month eligibility period.
Someone shouldn't have to be on the streets for 12 months to be eligible
for the Housing First policy. And this will also involve greater funding
for state and emergency housing.
Wouldn't that be a greater investment if we're to house people,
and help them transition back into permanent housing, than funding
for an inevitable increase to our prison population?
Because homeless people cannot pay fines because, once again, they are homeless.
If we're to look down that lens of what's greater value for taxpayer money,
then yeah, this is a greater investment.
So I guess to bring this to close, and kind of some comments for
reflection for this committee.
Why are we kicking people who are already down?
Our streets should be a safe place.
This is the completely wrong approach.
It is pretty obvious that the true cynical intention of the new move on
orders of this government is to clean up our streets for
tourists and international appeal.
Like Luxon on Newstalk ZB said that the biggest issue of the move on
orders is to
hope that Chuck and Mary have, when they go on their once in a lifetime trip to
Auckland, aren't intimidated in downtown Auckland.
So not actually thinking about the individual
welfare of people who are actually homeless. It's pretty horrendous.
And if we want to discuss international appeal,
kind of measuring our ability to hide the homeless is an appalling badge to
wear. But initiatives to relieve and end the homelessness
crisis that prioritize people is admirable.
Kind of at the end of the day as well,
homelessness reflects a failure of the state, right?
It reflects a failure of the state to ensure people have the means to
afford housing, whether it be by addressing systemic
inequities, especially amongst vulnerable groups such as Maori and Pasifika, who
are disproportionately over-represented
in our homeless population, or whether it be by ensuring wider housing
affordability.
It also reflects a failure of the state to intervene before that person's last
option is to live on the street. It is abhorrent to punish
homeless people for their position,
as the state itself holds a considerable level of responsibility to
prevent homelessness.
Okay, so yeah. Finally, housing is more than just a roof over one's head.
It provides people safety, it provides people dignity, protection,
health, stability, freedom, the means to build valuable lives.
So yeah, why not prioritize that?
And just closing, whakataukī. Ka
mate kainga tahi, ka ora kainga rua.
If a first home is no longer able to sustain the whanau, another can and must be
created so that person's well-being can be maintained. Kia ora.
Thanks, Charlie, and thank you, Sophie.
We've got a couple of people with questions. We'll start with Carl Bates.
Thanks very much, Chair, and thanks for the presentation to the Select Committee.
You've made the point that homelessness is being criminalized through this bill.
Why do you think that a number of submitters are politicizing this
when clearly the legislation doesn't criminalize whether or not someone
is homeless, it criminalizes not listening to the police and you
used the word cynical. Cynically, I suppose people would look
at submissions like yours and just think that they're politically
intended, as opposed to anything else,
because what it says on the tin
clearly doesn't
criminalize homelessness. Interested in your thoughts on that.
Yeah. Well,
clearly our submission is very values driven,
because we seriously care about these people on the street.
And the bill, though, literally describes
homelessness and homeless people as
people who can be issued a move on order.
So I'm not entirely sure where you're coming from from there, but is there anything
that-
But so you agree that it doesn't criminalize homelessness?
The legislation does not say if you are
homeless, you are a criminal.
But it describes homeless people, so it does
criminalize homelessness.
It doesn't criminalize homelessness. Thanks, Chair.
Okay, and a question from Dan Rosewarne.
Oh, yeah. Thanks for that submission, guys.
Other submitters have raised concerns about the geographical
scope of move on orders. And I was just wondering, in practical
terms, what problems do you think could arise if someone has
moved away from an area where they access healthcare,
social services, transports, or other types of
support?
Well, no, I might speak to that, actually.
With my experience through Take 10, we have some fantastic providers within
Wellington who do make a lot of effort.
For example, Maori Wardens and DCM who are in the central
city, that do foot patrols. A lot of what they do is keeping people
safe, and so that is probably why there's a lot of
homeless people are going towards city centers just for the sake of safety.
You can see towards, and especially in Wellington, areas like Newtown, a lot of
people sort of being pushed out that way.
It has just created a darker environment, a
more dangerous environment, and a less patrolled environment for their
safety as well. So at least in my experience,
for the most part, they are a lot safer in city centers, and that is where the
resources are. And I am concerned that if that wasn't there, they would not
be looked over, I guess, if that makes sense.
No, thank you. That's helpful.
Fantastic. Thank you, Charlie, and thank you, Sophie.
Really appreciate both of your time and your submissions to us today, and thank you
for joining us.
Cool. Thanks for the opportunities to speak on this. Thank you, everyone.
Thank you.
Okay, we're now going to come to Leonie.
Hey, Leonie. Thank you very much for joining us.
We have you down for a five-minute submission.
We have read your submission,
but please do leave a little bit of time at the end for questions. There you go.
You've just unmuted,
and hopefully we'll be able to see you at any moment.
But
five minutes, and we're in your hands.
Okay.
Sorry that you can't see me. It's probably a good thing. Wonder why.
Up here. No.
We can hear you. That's the main-
Okay
... we can hear you.
Okay. All right. Anyway, tena tatou
ko Leonie Ngoi.
I'm going to read from my submission, oral submission in order to keep me on
track.
I'm outraged that politicians in this country can
dream up such a shameful bill.
Another example of man's inhumanity to man.
There but for the good luck go you and I,
homeless on the street.
People who will never experience homelessness in their
lifetime will never know what homelessness is
like for, sadly, an increasing number of New Zealand
citizens, and politicians want to criminalize them for
that.
I grew up in an era where homelessness was unheard of,
and I cannot even recall ever seeing anyone homeless on the street.
Since the 1980s, with the spread of neoliberalism,
we had the Roger Douglas economics and Ruth
Richardson
legislations.
Political decisions have created the divide between those who have
and those who have not.
The current government has accelerated that divide.
The current prime minister did not even know there was no night shelter in
Auckland,
yet he backs the Move On bill.
Where are the homeless expected to move on to? Just around the corner?
There isn't anywhere for them to go.
Homelessness is a varied and very complex social
situation. At the heart of it is the
indifferent and poor decision-making by
politicians. This doesn't happen overnight.
For some people, especially our younger people, it may be the safest
place for them to be.
One of the clauses in the bill talks about failing to comply with move on
orders and has a penalty with a fine of up to
$2,000.
Well, I'd say good luck to them because homeless people don't have saving accounts.
Or there's a maximum penalty of up to three months in prison.
The average cost of an overnight stay in prison is $450 to
$500 per night.
Multiply that by 90 days, equals three months,
equals $40,500 per person.
How's that working for the economy?
As stated in my written submission, the police already have legislation which
enables them to deal with disorderly or offensive behavior.
Also, my written submission acknowledged the effect homelessness has on people's
business.
In my view, the government could divert the money spent on keeping people in
prison for the homeless to financially
supporting businesses to erect barrier doors across the frontage.
Just an idea.
Governments would do well to consider the increasing number of homeless people
and the impact this will have for our future society.
There needs to be some emotional intelligence applied here,
and do some long-term cross-party planning.
That's all I have to say.
Thank you, Leonie. Appreciate it.
I will just see if any members have a question for you.
There don't appear to be any, but thank you very much both for your written and
your oral submission today.
Thank you. Ngā mihi.
Thank you. Have a good evening.
Thank you.
Okay, we will now come to Pat.
And Pat will just be made as a
presenter.
Hi, Pat. Thank you for accepting. If you just wouldn't mind unmuting yourself
and turning your camera on.
We have you down for five minutes. We have read your submission,
but please do leave a little bit of time at the end for questions if members may
have them. Over to you, Pat
You've unmuted yourself, Pat. We just can't hear you.
Okay, we might come back to Pat. I'm not sure what's going on there.
But we will move to Janette McDonald or Jeannie.
I have seen that she is available and online.
So if we just bring Jeannie up.
Hey, Jeannie. Thank you for joining us. Great to have you with us.
As you will have heard in my instructions, we've got you for five minutes,
and we have read your submission. But please do leave a little bit of time at the
end for questions.
Over to you.
Yeah.
Kia ora. Kia ora, everybody. Kia ora koutou katoa.
I'm Janette, Jeannie, Janette McDonald of Māngere.
I oppose this bill entirely. The bill attempts
to address
anti-unsocial behavior in city streets by moving people
away from high-profile areas.
All the evidence is the bill won't work, and the existing legislation can
address the existing issues.
All sorts of people have told you this bill is contrary to the Bill of Rights and
the UN Charters that we've signed.
The bill targets vulnerable people who live in the streets and are
homeless. They have generally had tragic lives or a series of
really unfortunate occurrences.
There but by the grace of God go I, and you, if you didn't have any
income.
This bill will disproportionately affect people already
failed by the state and NGOs. That's why
they're on the streets.
They don't trust society, and they think we don't care,
frequently with reason.
They see no alternative.
They're disproportionately Maori or Pacifica, often with severe
physical or mental health issues.
They have likely to have suffered abuse, as my brother did.
He lived on the streets on and off from the ages of about
13 to his early 20s. He'd completely lost
trust in his adopted family and everyone else,
except for his friends on the streets maybe.
This had negative effects on both my brother and
our whole family,
and probably was a result of, as I said in the submission,
his being adopted into a Pakeha family. He's Maori.
He was looking for identity.
We failed him as a society.
The bill's provisions to young people are immoral and need to be
completely rethinked.
Moving on moves the problem elsewhere,
and if it is to the suburbs, then most of the support
services these people need are actually in the central
city. That's where the city missions are.
That's where most of the support is. That's where it's been concentrated.
We have homeless people here in Māngere.
They're not getting the help they need.
Mostly what's required is to build relationships because of the
broken trust.
The bill doesn't do that. It will make relationships with police
worse.
The bill criminalizes low-level unsocial
behavior. It penalizes poverty,
and the penalties for failing to comply with instructions from
this bill are laughable. If you had $500 or
$2,000 in your pocket, you might be able to find
accommodation.
And to put someone in prison, as the person immediately before
me said, well, that's amongst the most
expensive accommodation we have in the nation.
We should just do the sensible thing, provide some
wraparound services and
enough social housing.
I want to refer to a Ewan MacColl folk song
about the traveling people of Ireland, part of, well,
part of my history is Irish. I'm not going to sing it, unfortunately.
My husband, he's the singer. But I'll read a verse and then
the chorus.
"Born in the common of a building site, where the ground was rutted
by the trail of the wheels. The local Christian said to me,
'You'll lower the price of property.
Move along, get along, move along, get along. Go. Move.
Shift.'" I implore you to shift this
bill into the rubbish bin where it belongs.
Instead, put money and effort into wraparound services
and social housing and the many NGOs and people who've
spoken to you who are trying to do the good thing and
recognize the sacredness, the tapu, of all people
in this country.
Thank you, Jeannie. Thank you very much for your submission and for being with us.
We have reached your time limit there, but we do really appreciate both
your written and oral submission today, so thank you very much.
Sorry, I didn't realize. I'd practiced, but it clearly took a little bit longer.
You did a great job. So we're very appreciative. So thank you very much, okay?
This affects more than just the people who are homeless.
There are the families as well,
and broken relationships.
Thanks, Jeannie. Have a good evening. Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Okay. We're now going to come to Donald Grant.
Donald, if you can just unmute yourself, and if you've got a camera, switch that
on.
Donald
There we go. We can hear you, Don
Can you-- I thought my camera might be on, but is it not on?
It's not, but that's-
Oh, hang on. Sorry, I can just change this. Here we go.
That's what you look like. There you are.
Yes.
Testing.
Yes. Thank you very much. So thanks-
Got you down for five minutes
... thanks for this opportunity.
And I understand you've read my submission, so I certainly won't go through the
details of that. I have no specific role myself
with homelessness, but as noted in my submission, I have some
experience in making sure that government interventions meet the
objectives of government rather than undermining them.
And in my written submission, I did outline how this
bill will undermine the government's stated vision for housing and
urban development, which is that everyone lives in a home.
It certainly won't do anything to
address that whatsoever. Moving people, rough
sleepers in the street,
doesn't solve their homelessness at all.
But what it will undo with the apparent purpose
of this is to hide that homelessness so that the government
doesn't need to do anything about it.
And so therefore, it's counterproductive to the
government's stated vision, as I
mentioned. There's a couple of
other points that I wish to make. Oh, actually before
that, just a personal perspective.
My daughter and
also my wife, when we were living in Melbourne, did work to some extent
sort of volunteering with homeless people,
with what was called the Footpath Library,
which was providing books for homeless people
to read, and also donated glasses so that they could read them.
And I went there a couple of times and just spoke to some of the
people
who were there. They were people who had fallen on difficult circumstances, and it
became
obvious to me that someone like myself,
if circumstances were to change, could find
myself in that position. So my particular focus, I guess,
with this legislation is with
the application to homeless people and rough sleeping.
Subsequent to making that submission, so it wasn't mentioned in my
submission, just then became aware of
some government actions and initiatives that would
suggest that this bill is, in fact, not even intended to achieve
government objectives, but rather to avoid government
embarrassment by hiding the problem of homelessness,
moving it into a place where it is hidden,
where it cannot easily be counted.
And so the government would then be able to pretend
that they'd actually done something about it.
Some of those actions are the actions that have led to
increased unemployment, increased poverty, decreased social
housing. A recent example
is the cancellation of social housing, which was planned
for Port Chalmers.
And so the opportunities for providing
people with homes
within the housing and urban development vision is being
decreased rather than improved.
This leads to increased homelessness and rough sleeping, which the government
obviously finds
embarrassing. Also, a recent development or a recent
knowledge of a
development is the
government expectation that
emergency housing be reduced by 75%, and
directions to Ministry of Social Development staff and their
managers to ensure that
that happens with performance
management sanctions against staff who don't achieve those
objectives. So the Chief Executive of the Ministry of Social
Development has had to find a way to achieve
what is
essentially an unachievable
objective unless accompanied by cruelty.
This increases rough sleeping, the reduction of
emergency housing. The application of this bill
seems to be to make sure that the rough
sleepers are moved away from places where they're visible, places
where they can be counted, places where they can receive those
services, as previous speakers have spoken.
But also, in the case of my daughter and my wife, also
other volunteer services like the Footpath Library and
other opportunities that were given to
homeless people in Melbourne.
And I'm sure that there are similar sort of volunteer
services here in New Zealand.
So I also identified a scenario in
my submission in relation to the rights to
protest, the rights of association, the rights to freedom of
expression, freedom of movement,
in the situation where a homeless person peacefully
sleeping in a doorway, let's say, is issued with a move on
order by the police. And a group that supports
the homeless might wish to protest against that, might
choose for that protest to be in the location where they were
moved on, which would be a logical place for it,
and
ask that person to speak at it.
So I won't go into any more details
except to say that the
consequences if they do that, of course,
and it's
That which affects their rights under the Bill of
Rights Act.
As other speakers have also spoken, either
they get a $2,000 fine or move to prison, which is
extremely costly to the Crown. But other issues
as well, if they are moved to-
Don.
Sorry.
Sorry, Don. I do just need to stop you there.
We have gone quite significantly over-
Oh, sorry. Okay. Yeah
... allocated time. But if you just wanted to give us some last
couple of comments.
Yes. Well, so the last couple of comments, I suppose, my particular issue
is homelessness and rough sleeping.
And I guess I would also just ask the committee
to reflect on the question that if a
homeless person is sleeping peacefully in a doorway on
a closed business,
and they're woken up by police in the middle of the night and issued with a move on
order, who exactly is disturbing the peace?
And I'd like also to thank you for the opportunity to speak.
Thank you, Don. We really appreciate both your written and oral submission and
coming before us this afternoon as well. Thank you very much.
Thank you very much.
We're now going to have the Auckland Rainbow Community Church.
I know Peter's going to be back before us, who we saw a little bit earlier.
And we'll see if he's got any colleagues with him.
Kia ora tātou.
I should be joined by
my colleague, Professor Peter Lynham.
Here he comes.
If I'm not-
There he is. We've got you down for 10 minutes.
Please do leave a little bit of time at the end for some questions, and we have
read your submission. Okay?
Okay, cool.
Kia ora tātou. Ko Inura Fernando, tōku
ingoa.
Kia ora. I'm Inura from Auckland Rainbow Community
Church. I'm joined by the chair of our board,
Professor Peter Lynham.
So we came at this issue,
basically, we oppose it unequivocally.
We had two events this year.
One, a panel discussion
with Max Harris, Helen White, and
Danielle Lagale, as well as Jeremy
from Vision West on this move on orders.
And then we had
move on order submissions hui to encourage church
communities and
related people to oppose this bill.
Yeah. We
went into the details of arguments in their submission, so
it creates tangible harm for vulnerable people.
It tries to simplify very complex
issues,
and it's against that
Christian idea that
we're all God's children and we need to show love, and
compassion, and mercy. So it's a shameful,
disgraceful law.
Yes, so
maybe I'll
give opportunity for my colleague, Professor Peter Lynham, to
speak as well.
Thank you.
So
this matter was discussed by our board and discussed with our
members, and we were very privileged to be able to draw
a significant group of people from a range of churches at a meeting that
we organized in February,
which Inura has described. And then we had a session
a few weeks ago where we drew, again, quite
a significant panel of people, including social
workers and prominent lawyers. And the
critical thing I want to say is that we meet in the heart of the
city, in St Matthew's, right next door to HomeGround.
We do experience from time to time problems
with people who are drunk and disorderly and decide to
interrupt our meetings, and we have to handle that carefully, so we see the
problem. But what we've also seen is that simply
telling them to move on or imposing a fine or
a jail sentence on them does not further the process of
getting them out of the circumstances that have led them
into homelessness. I don't think anybody chooses
homelessness as a first option.
Fantastic. Okay. Well, thank you both.
We'll see if members have questions. We've got Dr Lawrence Sun first.
Kia ora. Thank you so much, Chair. Thank you, Inura and
Peter, for your submission.
I think that your submission's really
important because it highlights a particular sector of the community that might be
disproportionately affected
by this as well. Just want to check from what you're hearing
on the ground, how would this disproportionately
affect rainbow communities,
rainbow youth, rainbow seniors that are trans community?
Would you have any sort of anecdotal
information for us, for the committee?
I would say that
LGBT youth are at high risk of
homelessness, especially when they're in unsupportive families.
They also do experience mental health distress,
addictions,
a range of complex issues.
And it
may be an access point
for them into the justice system if these sort of
laws that profile or ... I used racial
profiling in my submission as well, but there could be other ways of
You know, creating disproportionate harm.
Because law is not the same if it's a
rich white person, privileged person, as opposed to a gay
person. There's intersectionality that you have to
consider.
We're particularly aware at the moment of the trans
community, and young trans people
frequently face really hostile treatment, end up on the
streets, and on the streets, they find themselves peculiarly
vulnerable to, I'm afraid, very
unkind and harsh treatment. So that is part of our
concern.
Fantastic. Thank you very much. See if any other members have questions.
Doesn't appear to be the case. So-
Sorry.
Oh, yes.
Just a follow-up question on that.
Just what you mentioned in the end, because one of the things we heard from
submitters is that if they move on, they
might be in a situation that's even less safe because it might
be less secure, et cetera.
Just what you mentioned right in the end on what do you mean for trans whanau in
that kind of-
Okay
... what are some of the concerns?
Yes, so the concerns are that, in fact, some of the people who
support homeless people, for example,
Lifewise,
and others like us who are in contact with people in
need, then can't find them because there's been quite
a fear going through the community, the homeless community, in the last few
weeks, actually. And they've just vanished,
often into new places, and without any location,
it's extremely difficult to provide support as is needed, and I think
Rainbow Youth in particular is finding this a struggle.
All righty. Thank you both. Nice to see you again, Peter, and thank you for your
time in making this submission and for joining us this afternoon as well.
Thank you.
Thank you so much.
Thank you. Now we're going to come to the New Zealand Police Association.
Oh, my apologies. I think,
actually, I might have jumped slightly ahead.
We're going to go back to Pat, who we were supposed to have a
little bit earlier, but I think we had
some...
Hi, guys. Just checking if you can hear me.
Yes, Pat, we can hear you if you want to continue your submission, please.
Okay. I apologize. I'm not sure why the video is
not working.
I'd just like to say,
tena koutou katoa,
chair and members of the Justice Committee.
Thank you for the opportunity to speak today.
My name is Pat Methemt, and I live in Wellington Central.
My perspective comes from four places: lived experience of
homelessness, professional frontline work supporting people who experience
homelessness, professional experience evaluating projects regarding
homelessness, and a master's degree in public policy.
In 2018, I was working as a professional tennis coach after years of high
performance playing coaching. After a
serious injury, I eventually had
to stop coaching, exhausted my savings, had to move out of my apartment, and
eventually found myself needing to move into the old Wellington Light Shelter on
Taranaki Street. I had no idea what to do, and had never been in such a
situation or scenario.
My experience taught me just how quickly someone's circumstances can change,
and just how difficult it is to get help when you need it.
I searched for help, but had no idea what to do, and it
was in a time when close family and friends were going through their own issues,
so I was on my own.
I remember my first meeting at MSD, where I was told by the caseworker that I
now--
where I told him that I had no money and needed help.
I was provided with no advice and given a payment card loaded up with $70
to pay for the night shelter for one week, which cost $10 a night.
Therefore, I had no idea where I would go for food or any other
way to survive. During the following period, I experienced tough and
dangerous conditions at the night shelter, rough sleeping on the
street, violence, fear, and a change in my mentality to purely trying
to survive each day, not knowing if I would still be alive the following day.
This is the daily fear, suffering, and uncertainty that many people
experiencing homelessness face every day.
Will I still be alive tomorrow? Why is the suffering so bad when I've done my best
to try and get help? What I experienced the winter shocked me to my core and
I fundamentally
changed the direction of my life with a strong passion to one day help improve
the situation and the people who are going through what I witnessed, and what
I've witnessed to somehow get worse since 2018.
Today, I would like to leave the committee with two messages.
First, I oppose this bill, but if it does get pushed through, it must be
amended so that people who are sleeping rough or begging purely as a means of
survival, and who are not behaving aggressively or causing
serious disruption, are not subject to move on orders.
I understand that a number of organizations and agencies have raised similar
concerns. The focus should remain on genuinely harmful
behavior, not on the simple fact that someone has nowhere else to go and is trying
to survive. The committee must also remember that people
acting aggressively or disruptive could not be due to receiving the
help which they need to receive. We must take ownership
for this problem, and that it has been created by ineffective and inefficient
policies to help our most vulnerable.
Second, I encourage the committee to focus less on
moving homelessness from one location to another and literally pushing the problem
down the street, but to start focusing on reducing homelessness itself.
My lived professional experience has taught me that homelessness does not
discriminate. It can happen to anyone when enough advanced
circumstances come together. Homelessness is not solved by moving
people on, it is solved by giving people a pathway forward.
As I mentioned in my written response, New Zealand reports one of the highest rates
of homelessness among OECD countries.
Other comparable countries have shown that long-term investment in prevention,
Housing First, wraparound support, and coordinated
services can reduce homelessness.
I believe New Zealand can do the same.
Do we want to be known as the country in the OECD who is the worst at taking
care of its most vulnerable? OECD data shows Finland's
reporter homelessness fell by almost half between 2017 and 2023,
continuing a longer-term decline.
It has made Housing First a sustained national strategy,
expanded permanent supported housing, converted shelters into housing,
and combined
accommodation with voluntary wraparound support.
I've been listening to
the submissions, and I keep hearing a question, what else can we do?
I'd like to echo what Vic Labor just mentioned.
The problem of homelessness has been dramatically
improved in other countries, and the investment of getting people off the street
and back into functional lives, often back into work, saving huge amount of
money in the long term by reducing the number of people who are homeless.
Finland is only one example of an economically comparable country to New Zealand as
a small, high-income OECD country with a very similar
population. New Zealand has implemented Housing First as a program.
Finland implemented Housing First as a national strategy.
That's the fundamental difference.
Its key policies include permanent housing without requiring sobriety or treatment
first, homelessness prevention and housing advice, affordable housing,
social housing
supply,
coordinated central government, municipal, and NGO delivery,
tailored health, addiction, and social support.
People experiencing homelessness are not someone else's problem.
They are our fellow New Zealanders.
We, as a country, created this, and we need to take responsibility for that and
start showing some empathy and genuine care for our fellow members of our society
who can make it back to a happy, functional life.
And with the right support, people can rebuild their lives.
I am proof of that. Finally, I respectfully think that members of this committee
need to understand homelessness and its reality, and I ask which members of this
committee would be willing to join me and spend 48 hours starting at 6:00 PM on a
Friday evening and ending on a Sunday evening at 6:00 PM, where we
would both have one set of clothing, one sleeping bag, no
cash whatsoever, one ID, and one drink bottle.
We would speak with members of the Wellington homeless community, do our best to
find food and somewhere to sleep, which may be the street.
Is anyone willing to do this? Thank you, and I appreciate your time and
invitation to speak.
Thank you, Pat. And we have exhausted your five-minute allocation with
us, but we do really appreciate both your written and your oral submission today.
So thank you for being with us.
We are now going to hear from the New Zealand Police Association, from their
president, Steve Watt.
Hi, Steve. Thank you for being with us. We have you down for 10 minutes.
We have read your written submission, and we would just ask
that you leave a few minutes at the end for questions that members may have.
I think you're still on mute at the moment.
If you can hear us, Steve, we just can't hear or see you at present.
And I might just ask advisors if they could just remove Pat as well,
please.
Ah, there we go.
There you go, Steve.
Hopefully that's better. Apologies there. A few technical difficulties.
We got there.
Kia ora, and thanks for having me. The New Zealand Police Association does
have serious concerns about the practicality and effectiveness of the proposed
move on order regime. The bill risks
placing police in a role of managing the visible effects of
homelessness, addiction, mental health issues, poverty,
and youth vulnerability, rather than addressing the underlying
causes. The bill is focused on displacement rather
than resolution. Police and our members already have
powers under the Summary Offences Act to address disorderly or offensive
behavior, assault and obstruction, property damage, and
graffiti. So we do question why additional powers
are needed when existing legislation already covers public
order offending.
We do have other concerns that relate to the practicalities of these
orders. For example, the bill does not specify where people must
go when moved on or how far away they must
relocate. This leaves significant discretion
with individual officers and creates uncertainty about enforcement.
People can return after 24 hours, potentially creating a cycle of
repeated enforcement against the same individuals.
And in many cases, like in central Auckland, there may be no
realistic or safe alternative accommodations available
for
rough sleepers.
We do worry about the resource and the operational impacts of the proposed
legislation. Repeated move on orders could divert frontline
officers from core policing functions such as prevention, response, and
investigations. And each order requires assessment,
recording, follow-up, and possible enforcement, making it resource
intensive. We do question what policing
priorities will be displaced if resources are
redirected to the move on orders.
We're significantly concerned also about the impact on young people.
The bill applies to children as young as 14 years old.
Our members are concerned this conflicts with youth justice principles
focused on welfare and rehabilitation.
Homeless and vulnerable youth may simply be repeatedly
displaced without receiving the support and accommodation, um,
or protection that they need.
There's also a lack of guidance, uh, with the bill.
There's no clear direction on appropriate destinations, handling
personal belongings, uh, of homeless people, follow-up actions,
referral pathways to support services, and it creates a, a
risk of inconsistency, arbitrariness, and, and legal
challenges. Um,
if the bill was to proceed, there are a number of recommendations that
we would make to this panel. There needs to be clear thresholds limiting
orders to genuine safety, harm, intimidation, obstruction,
or disorderly situations. There needs to be strong protections for
children and vulnerable people, and there also needs to be guidance for dealing
with homelessness, mental distress, addiction, and disability.
Referral pathways to housing, health, addiction, youth community services.
Mandatory reporting, um, of the requirements, and a
statutory review of the legislation after imple-
implementation. We do not believe at this stage the move
on orders will solve the underlying issues driving street
homelessness and public disorder.
Our primary concern is that police will be expected to repeatedly
relocate vulnerable people without the resources, services, or
legal guidance needed to achieve lasting outcomes. Thank you.
Fantastic. Well, thank you, Steve. We do have me- a few members with questions.
We'll start with Dr Lawrence Sun And.
Uh, thank you, Chair. Thank you, Steve, for your submission.
Um, one of the, the things that you might be answered, be able to answer.
So, we've heard so- from submitters that,
um, you know, the police have existing powers, and p- police can move
them on. But in situations where if they're trying to
move onto a different service and the service is not open,
what would police do in those kind of instances?
And that's the real crux of it here, because the legislation as it stands doesn't
give any direction as to what police should do in that circumstance.
So are they moving them two blocks down the street?
Are they having to move them to another suburb?
What is it or where is it that the officers dealing with the homelessness,
um, need to take these people or, or move these people onto?
There's no clear delineation in the, in the act as it, uh, currently
stands.
So not just in terms of the service, you know, moving them to a service,
et cetera, but even just moving them to another location is
unclear at this stage. Okay.
Yes.
Thank you so much.
All right. Uh, Camilla Belich.
Thank you. Thanks for your, um, submission, um, today as well in, in the detailed
recommendations. Um, I, I was concerned to hear
the comments that you made, um, in your written submission and also today around
resourcing. Uh, and I wanted to know, do you think that there is enough,
um, policing resource to be able to implement these
move on orders as they stand? And, and really a follow-up to that is, are you
concerned that, um, certain members of a community
may, um, begin to see begging and homelessness
as a, as primarily a policing issue and, you know, be calling,
uh, 111 to say that they've seen someone begging or seen someone,
um, homeless when that's, um, obviously may have a additional,
um, pressure on resourcing, uh, in
addition to the duties that may exist where there's a, when the bill
would actually genuinely apply?
Yeah, look, to answer the first part of your question, in reality, the police
only has limited resourcing when it comes to, um, our members
and the staffing out there. So when added pressure or another
focus h- has to be looked at, has to be policed, that will
take away from another area of policing, whether that's prevention, whether it's
investigations, whether it's turning up to the burglar at your home.
Uh, at the end of the day, police have limited resources in order to deal what they
have to deal with, and this just adds an extra complication,
an extra, um, uh, uh, you know, set of jobs
that our members will have to deal with.
In regards to the public and how they may view, um, police and
view the homelessness on the street, I did hear someone talk
about this a couple of speakers before, and they're right.
There will be an expectation from the public that police
deal with, um, homeless that are lying on the street
should the legislation pass in its current form.
'Cause that's specifically what it asks police to do, um,
is to remove homeless people, remove beggars from the street,
and there will be that expectation from the public to do so.
Thank you, Steve. And we've got one final question from Dan Rosewarm.
Yeah. Hey, thanks, Steve. I appreciate that.
That operational kind of context I think's been really helpful and, and
really rounded out our submissions quite well.
Uh, you, you say the bill risks placing police in a position of
managing the visible symptoms of homelessness, poverty,
addiction, and mental distress. And I was just wondering, in your view, where is
that line between a policing issue and a
social or housing issue, you think?
It's a really important point because you've got to look at it from the perspective
we've just withdrawn, or police have just withdrawn from the mental health
response, or slowly withdrawing from that.
Essentially what this bill does is almost draw us back into that,
because the reality is, is whilst not all homeless people
have, uh, mental health issues or, um,
financing issues, I would generally say the vast majority of them
do. So it draws us back into that whole, um,
social problem that really doesn't sit with police.
Uh, so,
the, the line is crossed I would suggest, um, with this legislation.
Thanks. That's helpful. Thank you.
Thank you, Steve, and really appreciate both your written and oral submission
today. So thanks for coming before us.
Kia ora. Thank you.
Great. Now we're going to see if Linda Ryan is online.
Hey, Linda. Thank you very much for joining us and for your patience.
Really appreciate it. Um, Linda, we have you down for 10 minutes to submit.
We have read your oral submission, but we would just ask that you just leave some
time at the end for some questions.
Kia ora. Thank you. Kia ora whānau.
My name's Linda Ryan, and I'm representing the Tākiri Mai Te Ata Whānau Ora
Collective Homelessness Prevention Services.
We're based out in Lower Hutt, AKA Ko Kirimari Seaview.
Um, we've been providing support for whānau who are, uh, rough
sleeping and who are requiring sustaining tenancy services,
mental health and addiction services, and financial mentoring for seven years.
We concentrate on delivering our services in Lower Hutt because
frankly, there's enough work for us to do with a team of 22 in the Hutt Valley.
Uh, we actually oppose the bill in its current form, and
we want to talk to you in simple ways. We want to show you the why.
We've written in our submission all the particular details, but I think I
want to start with a story of what it looks like for us on Mon- on a
Monday in our office. We're fortunate enough to have
a ICM, a, an MSD intensive case
manager, based in our office to work with our whānau who are
without shelter on a Monday. Uh, we have five
appointments available to work alongside Jackie, our
ICM. She's amazing. And our team are able
to provide a situation where we bring the whānau in to
see this MSD person. It's amazing.
That, that point of, uh, reference, uh, providing that support for whānau
on site has made a real difference for us.
But the cases we're seeing are getting sadder and sadder and more
complex. And the latest insights report from CHAR
have said that actually homelessness is the worst in our country than it's ever
been. And we can tell you from the ground that's actually the case.
Uh, the first one we got in last, uh, Monday arrived through our
clinics, a nae nae, a young mum, nine months hapu,
about to have baby, homeless in a car.
So we had to support that whānau through to a situation where
they could get into transitional housing, and we're trying now to get permanent
social housing. The next whānau was a
two-person situation with a tamariki of nine.
That whānau was also going from car to street to bridge to
car. And it was really, really raining that day, so
it was really sad when these whānau were turning up.
When they come into our office, often we're supporting whānau through the whole
day with a hot kai, clothes, those sorts of things, and we
don't put whānau back on the street.
We make sure we provide an opportunity for them to go into a
covered roof for the, for the evening, a few days until we can get them
permanently housed. The last whānau was the one who
really fits under this bill. They were living in a public street in a
broken down car where they'd built a,
a structure around the car. That person, because of the
broken car and because they
were undergoing some mental health crisis at the time, walked
to our offices in Seaview, which are a long way away from Lower Hutt City,
and they were soaking wet by the time they got here.
We provided them with a hot kai, the wraparound services,
saw MSD, warm, dry clothes. But I was with them
in the afternoon with one of my team, and a simple thing like putting them to,
into a motel for that night, which we actually funded, uh, with
a cake of soap and some food for the night.
The person was crying and crying and crying.
We're in that situation. We're seeing people like this every single
day. Having move on orders is just going to criminalize
this. It means people are going to go further down the street, go into harder
places to find, and after just listening to the
police, uh, submission, they're right.
There isn't the capacity to actually support these people when you're
finding them.
If a, a policeman turned up to us on a Monday and the team was
supporting four or five whānau, where is our capacity to pick up that
referral on the spot? Where is our capacity to treat
those people with the dignity they deserve, a warm, dry,
safe home?
Um, we oppose the bill in its current form or any other form.
We expect whānau in this country to be treated with dignity, and we ask that
the select committee oppose the bill as well. Thank you.
Thank you, Linda. And I'll just look to see if any members have any questions
for you.
Does not appear to be the case. That is no reflection, of course, on your
submission as well, Linda, so thank you very much.
Thank you. Bye.
Thanks for being with us this afternoon. Thank you.
Okay, members, we come to Amnesty Youth Otago,
Nico and Fergus,
our lucky last submitters on this bill for today
Kia ora. Can you hear me?
We can, and we can see you as well, and we can see Fergus too.
Yeah. Excellent.
Thank you both for being with us. You are our lucky last submitters today.
Best till last, I'm sure. You've got 10 minutes.
We've read your submission as well, so please do leave a little bit of time at the
end for questions as well.
Excellent. Will do. Thank you.
So kia ora, my name is Nico, and I'm the co-president of Amnesty Youth
Otago, and I'm joined by Fergus Marnedga, who's our schools
liaison. Amnesty Youth Otago is
the Otago University branch of Amnesty International, so we're a human
rights advocacy group.
And I'm just going to give you a brief outline of the structure of our submission.
So Fergus will first speak to our kind of broad position on the bill,
then I'll go into speaking on issues regarding freedom of speech.
Fergus will then address freedom of movement.
Lastly, I'll address issues regarding the impact the bill
will have on the homeless community, and then obviously we'll open up to questions.
But I'm also very happy to be interrupted throughout the submission as well.
Awesome. So over to you, Fergus.
Cool. So kia ora, my name is Fergus, as Nico said, and I'm the high school liaisons
officer. So Amnesty Youth Otago objects to the bill in its current form.
Fundamentally, we believe that there are already sufficient mechanisms to deal with
the behavior that is threatening or disorderly, as provided by
sections three and four of the Summary Offences Act.
The powers given to police under this bill to move people on is not
necessary to address these behaviors and infringes upon
individuals' freedom of movement and their ability to access important
services.
Furthermore, the bill allows for the moving on of people just begging or rough
sleeping, none of which interfere with the other person's use of public
spaces or their safety.
We therefore recommend that the bill not proceed or at the very least,
begging/rough sleeping be removed as a ground for issuing a move on
order. I'll pass to Nico to discuss begging further.
Awesome. Thank you, Fergus. So Amnesty Youth Otago submits that the
bill blatantly and unjustifiably infringes upon the
rights to freedom of expression, which is protected by Section
14 of the New Zealand Bill of Rights Act.
Begging is a form of expression. This was noted by the Attorney General in
his report, who stated that a person who is begging is conveying the
message, "I'm in need, and I'm requesting your help."
The right to freedom of expression
is protected for good reason. Freedom of expression is
fundamentally important to any democratic society.
Without it, we cannot claim to be free at all.
Much of the justification that has been provided for the bill has
concerned threatening and disorderly behavior.
So for example, in an interview, the Prime Minister gave the example of tourists
being confronted by a person sitting at a storefront, threatening at
them, shouting at them, and abusing them.
However, the definition of begging in clause four of the bill is quite broad and
is not restricted to begging that is disorderly or aggressive in
nature. A person could be issued a move on order therefore
for peacefully or even silently begging.
Because a person who fails to comply with the move on order commits a criminal
offense, the bill would in effect criminalize a peaceful form of
expression.
Another justification that has been used by the government for the ban on
begging is that it is necessary to support thriving urban economies.
We would like to ask though, how does a person peacefully begging actually
prevent an urban economy from thriving?
Because such a person, as we noted in our submission, is not disrupting passersby
or preventing them from entering shops.
In our view, it seems quite likely that the ban on begging serves to alleviate
the discomfort that some may feel when they see a person begging on the street.
However, that is not a sound reason to curtail a fundamental democratic
right.
There are many forms of expression that may offend certain people's
sensibilities. The beauty of living in a free and democratic
society is that these forms of expression are nevertheless
protected.
The rights to freedom of expression should only be curtailed for
exceptionally good reasons. That is recognized by Section
5 of BORA. The government has not provided any good
reasons. Over to you, Fergus.
Freedom of movement is a right guaranteed to all New Zealanders under the New
Zealand Bill of Rights Act.
It protects people's ability to pursue their own personal endeavors without
interference from the government.
Amnesty Youth Otago is concerned about individuals' freedom of movement being
interfered with by the bill. The bill gives wide-ranging powers to
police to move on individuals with limited restrictions.
There is no specification as to what a specified distance is,
nor are there carve-outs for entering an area which one has been moved on from
for important purposes such as going to a doctor or accessing
other essential services.
More guidance or restriction should be included as to what specified
distance means, and carve-outs for access to essential services
need to be included.
We do not consider the provision in Section 8F of the bill
that allows someone to breach a move on order if they have reasonable excuse to be
a sufficient enough carve-out, as it provides very little detail as
when one does have a reasonable excuse.
The law needs to be clear.
We also have concerns that rough sleeping being included as a ground for moving
someone on.
Rough sleeping in and of itself does not interfere with others' uses
of public spaces.
Public spaces are meant to be there for everyone, including those who may
be rough sleeping. Providing police with power to move on rough
sleepers prevents them from using public spaces that are meant to be for them.
Moving on rough sleepers will also likely see them moving further out of the CBD,
as there's insufficient night shelter capacity, as highlighted in the case of
Auckland, towards less well-lit, less trafficked,
and ultimately less safe areas.
I'll pass to Nico to discuss the further impact on the homeless.
Thank you, Fergus. So I lastly just briefly want to address the significant harm
that we believe this bill will cause to the homeless community.
Firstly, the move on orders process itself will obviously likely result in stress,
and could make the lives of homeless people more dangerous.
As I'm sure you've heard from previous submitters,
people occupy the center of towns and cities because they are the safest
places to be. They have lighting, there are other people in the homeless community
nearby, and there are central services nearby.
So I don't think it's necessary to elaborate too much on that, but that is
quite a key concern of ours. And I would also like to point out that it does not
appear that sufficient thought has gone into the true impact that the bill will
have on the homeless community.
Two weeks ago, well after this bill had been introduced to the House, the Prime
Minister admitted he didn't know there was no night shelter for rough sleepers in
Auckland.
The truth is that many people living on the street simply have nowhere else to
go. If they are moved on by the police, the question is
what exactly ought they to do?
We think the bill just doesn't address this core question
sufficiently. So in closing, AOL recommends that the bill
not proceed on the basis that it unjustifiably restricts the rights of New
Zealanders, is unnecessary, and will result in harm being caused to the
homeless community, and at the very least, that rough sleeping and begging should
be removed as grounds for issuing a move on order. Happy to take questions.
Thank you both, and really appreciate your oral submission.
I've got a question from Rima Naklay.
Yeah, hi gentlemen. Look, thanks for the submission, and I've asked this question
to a few people, still waiting for a sufficient answer.
What do I say to the member of my electorate who, he's
got a young family, and he's got a mortgage, and took a
risk and opened a restaurant. And there's
people that sit outside the restaurant, begging, rough sleeping,
and so patrons have said to him, "We love your restaurant, but I'm sorry mate, we
don't feel comfortable going in." So what do I say to that person?
What do we say to them?
Well, I need a bit more information on the specific circumstance.
So are the people who are outside, are they being aggressive and disruptive to
passers by? Are they blocking the access to the restaurant?
Sometimes. Not blocking, but aggressive.
Not blocking, but they're being aggressive still?
But not always aggressive. Sometimes they're just sitting there begging, like you
mentioned earlier.
Well, if they're just sitting there begging, then they're entitled to do so, as
they're in a public space.
Yes.
If they're being aggressive towards people, then that is already an offense under
the Summary Offenses Act that's on section four, I think.
Okay.
So that could be dealt with, and the police could visit and speak to them about
that.
Yeah. So then you can-
But that's our position. We don't think free speech should be violated, for
example-
But what about the restaurant owner, yeah? That has a mortgage to pay.
Yeah.
And people are telling you, "I'm sorry, we don't feel comfortable." You spoke about
discomfort. "We don't feel comfortable going into your
restaurant
while begging is taking place outside." What do I say to that
person that's trying to make a living for themselves?
You should say, I think, that look, the role of the
government, it's a balancing act.
We've got to balance the rights of different people in New Zealand.
And so yes,
it is difficult sometimes, but the government can't just
restrict the rights of others because it would be more profitable for
yourself, and it would help you pay off your mortgage.
I know that's difficult to hear, but certain things can't be
interfered with, such as people's right to free expression and free movement,
right? Because the government could do lots of things that would be good for the
economy, perhaps.
For example,
the government could
lock up anyone who shoplifted, ever.
They never see the
light of day.
And perhaps that would mean that shoplifting would not happen so much.
But that would be a gross violation of their rights.
So it's a balancing act in terms of the rights of different people, and the
government can't just use a hammer to deal with quite a delicate
solution. That's my response.
Okay. Thank you.
Thank you. We have reached our time limit, and thank you to
both of you guys for your written and oral submission, and for joining us this
afternoon. So thank you very much.
Thank you very much.
Members, that ends our time on the Summary Offenses Move on
Order Amendment Bill for today. We will pick up oral
submissions on that again on Friday.
But we are moving to the Corrections Management of Prisoners and Prisoners Property
Amendment Bill, with the Office of the Ombudsman.
We've already heard all of the other submissions on the bill, and this is
just the Ombudsman's chance to submit to us, with him
not being available on the two previous days that we did hear submissions.
So,
John, Stewart, and who is the
third gentleman with-
Nick.
Nick. Great to have you both with us this afternoon. Thank you for joining us.
You have 10 minutes. Thank you.
Kia ora tatou, and thank you, Mr. Chairman, for the opportunity to submit,
notwithstanding my unavailability, which
was the consequence of a bereavement within my family.
So I'm sorry not to have been appearing
earlier. This is obviously an important piece of legislation
that's described in the explanatory note as a framework
piece of legislation, in the sense that it's amending the
Corrections Act. And it's amending the
Corrections Act
to reflect what is, in some respects,
a changed set of circumstances being faced
by Corrections, and the realities of the impact
of some of the new types of prisoners that
they have within the prisons. And we absolutely
understand
And respect the pressures that are being felt by
corrections and the challenges that they are facing.
But I want to be very clear that this proposed
amendment does not change the
foundational principles of the Corrections Act
as expressed in sections five and six.
And as you will be well aware as a committee,
those principles include the requirement that no
sentence is administered
more restrictively
than it needs to be.
And in our view, and you'll have read this in our
submission,
both the establishment of the new designations
for prisoners,
and the new arrangements around the
potential segregation of prisoners
draw on what I would describe as loose and
inadequate language,
which makes it extraordinarily difficult for either the chief
executive in the case of designated prisoners, or the
managers of prisons around our country,
to be able to reach reasonable judgments
about whether or not those orders should be
imposed. And you will have read, and had read
to you I don't doubt,
the provisions of the relevant sections.
You will have seen that what is required by the chief
executive, albeit he'll be supported by recommendations from a
panel,
is a level of prescience about what might occur
in some future circumstance
as a consequence of a particular prisoner being held
within the prison. And while I don't doubt that the chief
executive will be able to draw on a range of
information to help inform her or his
decision,
my view
is that the way in which that language is
framed
is too broad,
and that the levels of protections that are
available is insufficient
to ensure that the principles of the
act are actually being abided with.
That is also true in relation to the
segregation provisions. It's largely the same
language, although obviously the obligation or
the issue of participation in a
criminal gang or criminal organization is
added in the segregation provisions
rather than in the designation provisions.
But again, we're asking managers of prisons to look
into the future, to cast their minds into the future, and
make an assessment about the circumstances that are
going to pertain in relation to a particular
individual. And the consequences of that
decision being taken either by the chief executive or
by the individual prison manager
are real and significant
for the individual concerned.
You will, I'm sure, have visited prisons where this particular
regime or regimes similar
are currently being applied. You will have seen, as I have,
the levels of restriction that are being applied.
And I think it's impossible to have been and seen and heard and
talked, and not to be concerned about the
expansion of this type of regime across our
prison system.
There are, of course, challenges.
But in my view,
the language, the guardrails are not sufficiently
established in this legislation to enable us to
be confident that it will be able to be
appropriately applied against the wider
principles that define our treatment of prisoners
in prisons.
Lastly, I'll just say that there is
significant emphasis placed in this
legislation or this proposed legislation
on the definitions and approach to be
taken to something called meaningful human contact.
And meaningful human contact is important because
if you lock somebody up for more than 22 hours a day and they
don't have meaningful human contact, they
are in solitary confinement for that day.
And if that solitary confinement lasts for more than 15 days,
then the Mandela principles and the international law
says that
that is an inappropriate
and illegal use
of solitary confinement.
The impact of solitary confinement and of
segregation
is alluded to in the explanatory note.
The damage that can be done is alluded to in the explanatory
note. And while there will be limited circumstances
where no doubt
limitations need to be imposed, in our view,
the expansion of this remit in this
way with so few checks and
balances,
particularly in the context of prison managers
segregating prisoners, the requirement for them to
guess about the future and assess risk on
risk into the future in many instances
Is simply inappropriate against the
principles that we as a country have not
only decided on, but is reflected in our law
and in international law.
So I'm happy to answer any questions you may have. You'll have read the submission.
Obviously, it goes into a wider range of subject areas than I've been
able to cover this afternoon. Again, I'm very
grateful for the opportunity to appear.
Thank you, John, and thank you for submitting with us today.
We do have a question from Camilla Belich.
Thank you, and thank you
for the submission and the written submission.
So I just have two questions
for you. The first one is,
I previously asked at another select committee that you were appearing in front of
if the legislation as proposed had addressed the
concerns that your predecessor had raised in his report.
What I've taken from what you've said today and in
the written submission is that it doesn't sufficiently
address the concerns raised by your predecessor.
So that's the first question. And the second question I have is around the
Mandela Rules.
I think it's in our Crimes Act, we
have the Mandela Rules referenced
in relation to the
obligations and the object of the act, and
my understanding is that means that they are currently part of our
domestic legislation. And so I wanted to know,
in your view, does this bill
restrict and limit, apart from the instance which you've just covered
or maybe you want to touch on that again,
the application of the Mandela Rules to New Zealand?
So Sir Peter, in his report that you're
referring to,
was principally concerned about the way in
which the restrictive practices that he was
investigating were being applied.
And his concerns extended to how
people were being incarcerated
according to those stricter rules,
and importantly, how they were getting out of
that state of incarceration.
And he was particularly concerned that prisoners did not
know what they needed to do, if they could do
anything at all,
to end their period of incarceration under the more formal
regime.
In my view, many of the issues that he has
raised continue under this legislation.
It is useful to have parts of it
reflected in legislation rather than simply in practice and
custom. So that is undoubtedly a step forward.
But it is a real concern to me
to see what is effectively an
embedding, in my view, of a process of
segregation
as a normal tool of the operation of our prisons,
rather than a last resort or a limited tool,
as is seen under the Mandela Rules.
So to answer your question very directly, no, I do not
believe that this legislation adequately or
completely addresses the concerns raised by Sir Peter.
I believe that those concerns continue, and that is
largely because of the broadness of
the discretions that are being given
to both the
chief executive and the manager of prisons.
And my concern is that when they are under pressure, and they
are, and they are under pressure in a real way because of
population and all the things you know about,
the
opportunity to use that discretion
adverse to a prisoner is going to be heightened.
And so that is a concern in my mind.
So that's the first question.
The second question in terms of the domestic application
of the
Mandela Rules. Look, I haven't read the Crimes Act in the last
few evenings, so I can't give you a specific answer to that,
although Nick or Stuart might be able to.
I'm happy to briefly answer it.
In a previous report Sir Peter did, Kōkiri Whaitaki, we did pick
up this issue of how the Corrections Act references the Mandela Rules, and we did
point out that the act at the moment references the rules in
quite an indirect way, so it doesn't directly incorporate the rules.
And again, our written submission on this point of solitary
confinement is that it is not consistent with what the Mandela Rules
require. And I think in the explanatory note,
it kind of acknowledges that that's the case in saying that the provisions are
partly based on Mandela Rules. So they're not a direct reflection of what
those rules require.
Those rules require 14 days, two weeks,
as a minimum, and we're looking at 10.
10 hours, yeah.
Okay.
10 hours. 14 days, 14 hours.
Could I just ask one supplementary?
Just quickly, we are significantly over time.
Oh, sorry. I suppose my overall question, I think it was the Corrections Act, so
thank you for... It's been a long day, so thank you for correcting me.
I suppose my overall point was, does
this act worsen the status quo in relation to the
application of the Mandela Rules?
Yes, I think so. In terms of what I've just described,
yes it does. It is a step
back, and is a step beyond what we understand
the Mandela Rules to be saying.
Fantastic. Well, thank you very much, John, Stuart, and Nick.
We appreciate you joining us late this afternoon, so thank you very
much, and thank you for your submission as well.
Thank you.
Members, we have
already instructed to prepare a departmental report, so we will progress in that
sense.
Mr. Chair-
We will need to move to the private...
I think that's what Maggie was about to tell me, but we will just move to our
private link now, please.